<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!--
-
- phpMyAdmin XML Dump
- version 2.9.1.1
- http://www.phpmyadmin.net
-
- Host: 10.6.171.42
- Generation Time: Oct 14, 2008 at 01:25 PM
- Server version: 4.1.22
- PHP Version: 4.4.4
-->

<!--
- Database: 'citizensmarket'
-->
<citizensmarket>
  <!-- Table categories -->
    <categories>
        <cat_id>1</cat_id>
        <cat_name>Economic Development</cat_name>
    </categories>
    <categories>
        <cat_id>2</cat_id>
        <cat_name>Environment</cat_name>
    </categories>
    <categories>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
        <cat_name>Labor Practices</cat_name>
    </categories>
    <categories>
        <cat_id>4</cat_id>
        <cat_name>Corporate Gvoernance</cat_name>
    </categories>
    <categories>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <cat_name>Civil Society</cat_name>
    </categories>
    <categories>
        <cat_id>6</cat_id>
        <cat_name>Impact on Conflict &amp; Indigenous Communities</cat_name>
    </categories>
    <categories>
        <cat_id>7</cat_id>
        <cat_name>Product Responsibility</cat_name>
    </categories>
    <categories>
        <cat_id>8</cat_id>
        <cat_name>Other</cat_name>
    </categories>
  <!-- Table co_keyword -->
  <!-- Table company -->
    <company>
        <co_id>2</co_id>
        <co_name>Chevron</co_name>
        <ind_cd>Petroleum Refining</ind_cd>
        <comments>Chevron is ranked in Fortune’s 2007 Global 500 as the 7th largest company in the world and the 4th largest company in the Petroleum Refining industry, with $200+ billion in revenues.  The company is headquartered in San Ramon, California, USA and is active in more than 180 countries.</comments>
        <brands>Chevron, Texaco, Caltex, Gulf, Arteco, Delo, Havoline, ParaLux, Oronite, Pro-Gard, Revtex, Techron, Ursa, Xpress Lube</brands>
    </company>
    <company>
        <co_id>5</co_id>
        <co_name>Royal Dutch Shell</co_name>
        <ind_cd>Petroleum Refining</ind_cd>
        <comments>Royal Dutch Shell is ranked in Fortune’s 2007 Global 500 as the 3rd largest company in the world and the 2nd largest company in the Petroleum Refining industry, with $318+ billion in annual revenues.  The company is headquartered in The Hague and in London.</comments>
        <brands>Shell</brands>
    </company>
    <company>
        <co_id>12</co_id>
        <co_name>Procter &amp; Gamble</co_name>
        <ind_cd>Household &amp; Personal Products</ind_cd>
        <comments>Procter &amp; Gamble is ranked in Fortune’s 2007 Global 500 as the 74th largest company in the world, with $68+ billion in annual revenues.  The company is headquartered in Cincinnati, Ohio, USA.</comments>
        <brands>Ace, Activair EasyTab, Actonel, Align, Always, Ammens, Ariel, Asacol, Attento, A Touch of Sun, Aussie, Ayudin, Az, Baldessarini, Balsam Color, Bess, Blend-a-dent, Blend-a-med, Blendax, Bold, Bonus, Bonux, Boss, Bounce, Bounty, Braun, Bruno Banani, Buffette, Camay, Cascade, Charmin, Cheer, Cheff, Children’s Pepto, Cierto, Clairol, CoverGirl, Crest, Cristal, Cutie, Dantrium, Daily Defense, Dash, Dawn, Daz, Didronel, Dodot, Downy, Dreft, Duracell, Enablex, Ela, Era, Escada, Escudo, Eukanuba, Evax, Fairy, Febreze, Fibersure, Fixodent, Folgers, Frost &amp; Tip, Gain, Ghost, Gillette, Gleem, Hairpainting, Head &amp; Shoulders, Herbal Essences, Hipoglos, Home Café, Hugo, Hydrience, Iams, Infasil, Infusium, Inner Science, Ipana, Ivory, Jar, Joy, Kolestone, Kukident, Lacoste, Ladysan, Laura Biogiotti, Lavasan, Lenor, Lines, Linidor, Loreto, Loving Care, Lunch, Luvs, Macrobid, Macrodantin, Maestro, Magia Blanca, Magistral, Max Factor, Men's Choice, Metamucil, Millstone, Miss Clairol, Motif, Mr. Clean, Mr. Proper, Mum, Muse, Myth, Naomi Campbell, Natural Instincts, Naturella, Nice 'n Easy, Noxzema, Olay, Old Spice, Oral-B, Pampers, Pantene, Pepto-Bismol, Perla, Pert Plus, Physique, Pop, Prilosec OTC, Pringles, Puffs, Puma, PUR, Rejoice, Rejoy, Rindex, Safeguard, Salvo, SatinCare, Scope, Secret, Senior, Shockwaves, SK-II, Supremo, Sure, Swiffer, Tampax, Tempo, Tess, Tide, Tras, Thermacare, Ultress, Unijab, Valentino, Vencedor, Viakal, Vicks, Vitapyrena, Vizir, Wella, Whisper, Wick, XtremeFX, Yes, Zest, Zooth</brands>
    </company>
    <company>
        <co_id>3</co_id>
        <co_name>ConocoPhillips</co_name>
        <ind_cd>Petroleum Refining</ind_cd>
        <comments>ConocoPhillips is ranked in Fortune’s 2007 Global 500 as the 9th largest company in the world and the 5th largest company in the Petroleum Refining industry, with $172+ billion in annual revenues.  The company is headquartered in Houston, Texas, USA.</comments>
        <brands>Conoco, Phillips 66, 76, COOP, JET, Kendall, ProJet, Turkpetrol</brands>
    </company>
    <company>
        <co_id>1</co_id>
        <co_name>BP</co_name>
        <ind_cd>Petroleum Refining</ind_cd>
        <comments>BP, formerly known as British Petroleum, is ranked in Fortune’s 2007 Global 500 as the 4th largest company in the world and the 3rd largest company in the Petroleum Refining industry, with $274+ billion in annual revenues.  The company is headquartered in London.</comments>
        <brands>BP, ampm, Aral, Arco, Castrol, Wild Bean Coffee</brands>
    </company>
    <company>
        <co_id>4</co_id>
        <co_name>ExxonMobil</co_name>
        <ind_cd>Petroleum Refining</ind_cd>
        <comments>ExxonMobil is ranked in Fortune’s 2007 Global 500 as the 2nd largest company in the world and the largest company in the Petroleum Refining industry, with $374+ billion in annual revenues.  The company is headquartered in Irving, Texas, USA and is active in more than 180 countries.</comments>
        <brands>Exxon, Mobil, Esso, On the Run, Speedpass</brands>
    </company>
    <company>
        <co_id>6</co_id>
        <co_name>Sinopec</co_name>
        <ind_cd>Petroleum Refining</ind_cd>
        <comments>Sinopec, or China Petroleum and Chemical Corporation, is ranked in Fortune’s 2007 Global 500 as the 17th largest company in the world and the 7th largest company in the Petroleum Refining industry, with $131+ billion in annual revenues.  </comments>
        <brands>Sinopec, Gaoqiao Petrochemical, Udmurtneft</brands>
    </company>
    <company>
        <co_id>7</co_id>
        <co_name>Total</co_name>
        <ind_cd>Petroleum Refining</ind_cd>
        <comments>Total is ranked in Fortune’s 2007 Global 500 as the 10th largest company in the world and the 6th largest company in the Petroleum Refining industry, with $168+ billion in annual revenues.  The company is headquartered in Paris.</comments>
        <brands>Total, Atotech, Bostik, Cook Composites &amp; Polymers, Cray Valley, GPN, Hutchinson, Rosier Fertilizers, Sartomer, Totsa</brands>
    </company>
    <company>
        <co_id>8</co_id>
        <co_name>Colgate-Palmolive</co_name>
        <ind_cd>Household &amp; Personal Products</ind_cd>
        <comments>Colgate-Palmolive has $13 billion in annual revenues.  The company is headquartered in New York City, New York, USA.</comments>
        <brands>Afta, Ajax, Bambeanos, Caprice, Cashmere, Colgate, Crystal White Octagon, Darlie, Dermassage, Evitol, Fabuloso, Fleecy, GARD, Hill’s, Irish Spring, Mennen, Murphy Oil Soap, Odex, Ola, Palmolive, Pinho Sol, Polyana, Pom Pom, Protex, Skin Bracer, Softsoap, Sorriso, Soupline, Speed Stick, Suavitel, Tandy, Teen Spirit, Tom's of Maine</brands>
    </company>
    <company>
        <co_id>9</co_id>
        <co_name>Henkel</co_name>
        <ind_cd>Household &amp; Personal Products</ind_cd>
        <comments>Henkel is ranked in Fortune’s 2007 Global 500 as the 471st largest company in the world, with $15+ billion in annual revenues.  The company is headquartered in Dusseldorf, Germany.</comments>
        <brands>20 Mule Team, 4+4, Adhesin, Alodine, Antica Erboristeria, Aok, AromaSense, Autophoretic, Bac, Barnangen, BC Bonacure, Bonderite, Bonderlube, Bref, Ceresit, Coast, Citre Shine, Clynol id, Combat, Country Colors, Denivit, Dep, Diadermine, Dial, Dorus, Dry Idea, DTI, Euromelt, Fa, Frekote, Gerolub, Got2b, Granocoat, Henkel, Hysol, Igora, Indola, Innova, L.A. Looks, La Toja, Licor del Polo, LineGuard, Liofol, Loctite, Macroplast, Metylan, Mir, Miracure, Mont Saint Michel, Multan, Multicore, Natural &amp; Easy, Natural Styling, Neutromed, omniFIT, Optal, Osis, P3, Palette, Pattex, Persil, Perwoll, Poly, Ponal, Pril, Purex, Purmelt, Renuzit, RGX, Right Guard, Rubson, Sanicare, Schauma, Schwarzkopf, Scorpio, Seah, Seborin, Sicomet, Silhouette, Smooth ‘N Shine, Soft &amp; Dri, Soft Scrub, Somat, Sil, Sista, Spee, Strait Styling, Taft, Technomelt, Terocore, Terolan, Terophon, Teroson, Terostat, Theramed, Thicker Fuller Hair, Tone, Turco, UniBond, Vademecum, Vernel, Viton, Zero Frizz, Zout</brands>
    </company>
    <company>
        <co_id>10</co_id>
        <co_name>Kimberly-Clark</co_name>
        <ind_cd>Household &amp; Personal Products</ind_cd>
        <comments>Kimberly-Clark is ranked in Fortune’s 2007 Global 500 as the 437th largest company in the world, with $16+ billion in annual revenues.  The company is headquartered in Irving, Texas, USA.</comments>
        <brands>Andrex, Camelia, Cottonelle, Depend, Drynites, GoodNites, Hakle, Huggies, Intimus Gel, JRT, KC Professional, Kimberly-Clark, KIMCARE, KIMTECH, KleenBébé, KLEENGUARD, Kleenex, Kotex, KREW, Lidie, Little Swimmers, Naturally Tuff, Neve, PeauDouce, Pétalo, Pingos, Plenitud, Poise, Pull-Ups, REFLECTIONS, Scott, Scottex, Snugglers, Subtelle, Thick &amp; Thirsty, Viva, Wondersoft, WYPALL</brands>
    </company>
    <company>
        <co_id>11</co_id>
        <co_name>L'Oreal</co_name>
        <ind_cd>Household &amp; Personal Products</ind_cd>
        <comments>L’Oréal is ranked in Fortune’s 2007 Global 500 as the 353rd largest company in the world, with $19+ billion in annual revenues.  The company is headquartered in Clichy, France.</comments>
        <brands>Biotherm, Cacharel, Garnier, Giorgio Armani, Helena Rubinstein, Innéov, Kérastase, Kiehl’s, Lancôme, La Roche-Posay, Le Club des Créateurs, L’Oréal, Matrix, Maybelline NY, Mizani, Ralph Lauren, Redken, Shu Uemura, SkinCeuticals, Softsheen-Carson, Vichy, Viktor &amp; Rolf</brands>
    </company>
    <company>
        <co_id>13</co_id>
        <co_name>The Clorox Company</co_name>
        <ind_cd>Household &amp; Personal Products</ind_cd>
        <comments>The Clorox Company has $4+ billion in annual revenues.  The company is headquartered in Oakland, California, USA.</comments>
        <brands>Anywhere, Arco Iris, Arela, ArmorAll, Astra, Ayudin, Bluebell, Bon Bril, Brita, Chux, Clorinda, Clorox, Emperatriz, Ever Clean, EverFresh, Formula 409, Fresh Step, Glad, Gladware, Gumption, Handi-Wipes, Handy/Andy, Hidden Valley, KC Masterpiece, Kingsford, Kitchen Bouquet, Lestoil, Limpido, Liquid-Plumr, Los Conejos, Lustrillo, Mistolin, Mono, Mortimer, OSO, Oxi Magic, Pine-Sol, Pinoluz, Poett, Prestone, Scoop Away, S.O.S., STP, Tilex, Wash’n Dri, XLO, Yuhanrox</brands>
    </company>
    <company>
        <co_id>14</co_id>
        <co_name>Unilever</co_name>
        <ind_cd>Household &amp; Personal Products</ind_cd>
        <comments>Unilever is ranked in Fortune’s 2007 Global 500 as the 120th largest company in the world, with $51+ billion in annual revenues.  The company is headquartered in London and Rotterdam.</comments>
        <brands>Ades, Adez, Aim, Ala, Algida, All Clear, Alsa, Amino, Amodent, Amora, Andrélon, Annapurna, Arisco, Axe, Ayush, Baba, Becel, Ben &amp; Jerry's, Bertolli, BiFi, Blue Band, Blue Bonnet, Bonella, Boursin, Bovril, Breeze, Bresler, Breyers, Brilhante, Brooke Bond, Bru, Brunch, Brut, Bushell’s, Cajoline, Calvé, Caress, Carte d’Or, Choysa, Cica, Cif, Citra, Clear, Clinic, Close Up, Coccolino, Colman's, Comfort, Conimex, Continental, Coral, Cornetto, Country Crock, Crème Bonjour, Cremissimo, Dante, Degree, Delma, Domestos, Doriana, Dove, Drive, Du Darfst, Effi, Elida, Elidor, Elmlea, Fair &amp; Lovely, Findus, Florz, Fofo, Friol, Fruitrience, Frytol, GB Glace, Geisha, Glen, Globus, Glorix, Good Humor, Hamam, Hazeline, HB Ice Cream, Heartbrand, Hellmann’s, Hera, Hertog, Iberia, I Can't Believe It's Not Butter, Iglo, Imperial, Impulse, JB, Jif, Kasia, Kecap Bango, Key Soap, Kibon, Kissan, Klinex, Klondike, Klover Vaseline, Knorr, Komili, Kuner, Kuschel Weich, Kwality, Lady’s Choice, Lady Gay, Lakmé, Lan-Choo, Langnese, Latta, Lawry’s, Lever 2000, Lifebuoy, Lipton, Liril, Lux, Lyso, Lynx, Lyons, Magic, Magnum, Maizena, Maille, Malloa, Marmite, Maya, Mazola, Mentadent, Miko, Milda, Minerva, Mondamin, O’hoj, Omo, Organics, Pears, Pfanni, PG Tips, Peperami, Pepsodent, Persil, Planta, Pond’s, Popsicle, Pot Noodle, Primavera, Pro-Activ, Promise, Pummarò, Pureit, Q-Tips, Quix, Radiant, Ragú, Raguletto, Rama, Razar, Rexena, Rexona, Rin, Rinso, Robyn, Royco, Saga, Sana, Sanella, Santa Rosa, SariWangi, Savora, Scottish Blend, Seda, Sedal, Shedd’s Spread, Signal, Skip, Skippy, Slim-Fast, Slotts, Snuggle, Soft, Sol, Solero, Solo, Stork, Suave, Sun, Sunil, Sunlight, Sunsilk, Supreme, Surf, Svelto, Taro, Té Ati, Té Club, Thea, ThermaSilk, Timotei, Unilever Food Solutions, Ultrex, Unox, Vaseline, Vasenol, Via, Vinólia, Viennetta, Vim, Viss, Vivere, Wall’s, Wheel, Winborgs, Wish-Bone, Wisk, Yumos, Zed, Zwan</brands>
    </company>
  <!-- Table industry -->
  <!-- Table issue -->
    <issue>
        <top_id>12</top_id>
        <top_name>Research &amp; Development</top_name>
        <desc>(Renewable Energy, Sustainable Products &amp; Services)</desc>
        <cat_id>2</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>39</top_id>
        <top_name>Other</top_name>
        <desc>other issues not represented elsewhere</desc>
        <cat_id>0</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>15</top_id>
        <top_name>Conservation</top_name>
        <desc>(Materials Used, Recycling, Energy, Water, Transport)</desc>
        <cat_id>2</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>16</top_id>
        <top_name>Emissions, Effluent &amp; Waste Management</top_name>
        <desc>(Greenhouse Gas Emissions, Ozone Depletion, Solid Waste and Wastewater Disposal, Spills)</desc>
        <cat_id>2</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>17</top_id>
        <top_name>Biodiversity</top_name>
        <desc>(Impact on Habitats and Protected Areas)</desc>
        <cat_id>2</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>18</top_id>
        <top_name>Corruption &amp; Bribery</top_name>
        <desc>(Illegal Influence: Incidences, Oversight, Training, Response)</desc>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>19</top_id>
        <top_name>Public Policy</top_name>
        <desc>(Legal Influence: Lobbying, Political Contributions)</desc>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>20</top_id>
        <top_name>Anti-Competitive Behavior</top_name>
        <desc>(Anti-Trust, Monopoly Practices)</desc>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>21</top_id>
        <top_name>Executive Compensation</top_name>
        <desc>(Executive Pay &amp; Benefits, Golden Parachutes)</desc>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>22</top_id>
        <top_name>Investment &amp; Procurement Practices</top_name>
        <desc>(Sustainability Screening for Suppliers and Investment Agreements, Employee Training) </desc>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>23</top_id>
        <top_name>Security Practices</top_name>
        <desc>(Operations in Conflict Zones, Complicity With Repressive Governments or Paramilitary Groups)</desc>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>24</top_id>
        <top_name>Indigenous Rights</top_name>
        <desc>(Land Appropriations and Other Violations of Rights of Indigenous Peoples)</desc>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>25</top_id>
        <top_name>Reporting &amp; Disclosure</top_name>
        <desc>(Transparency, Quality of Corporate Citizenship Reports and Publicly Available Data)</desc>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>26</top_id>
        <top_name>Economic Performance</top_name>
        <desc>(Money Generated &amp; Distributed, Financial Assistance from Government)</desc>
        <cat_id>1</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>27</top_id>
        <top_name>Market Presence</top_name>
        <desc>(Wages Compared to Local Minimum Wage, Use of Local Suppliers &amp; Local Hires)</desc>
        <cat_id>1</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>28</top_id>
        <top_name>Indirect Economic Impacts</top_name>
        <desc>(Infrastructure Development, Other Indirect Impacts)</desc>
        <cat_id>1</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>29</top_id>
        <top_name>Employment Stability &amp; Benefits</top_name>
        <desc>(Workforce Turnover, Family Benefits, Child Care, Retirement, Health Care, Profit Sharing)</desc>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>30</top_id>
        <top_name>Labor/Management Relations</top_name>
        <desc>(Unions, Freedom of Association and Collective Bargaining)</desc>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>31</top_id>
        <top_name>Occupational Health &amp; Safety</top_name>
        <desc>(Injury &amp; Fatality Rates, Prevention Measures)</desc>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>32</top_id>
        <top_name>Training &amp; Education</top_name>
        <desc>(Performance Reviews, Professional Development, Managing Career Endings)</desc>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>33</top_id>
        <top_name>Diversity &amp; Equal Opportunity</top_name>
        <desc>(Parity in Wages and Executive/Board Representation, Cultural Competence, for Minorities, Women, LGBT, People With Disabilities)</desc>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>34</top_id>
        <top_name>Forced, Compulsory or Child Labor</top_name>
        <desc>(Slavery, Human Trafficking, Child Labor)</desc>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>35</top_id>
        <top_name>Customer Health &amp; Safety</top_name>
        <desc>(Quality Assurance, Consumer Illnesses/Injuries/Fatalities)</desc>
        <cat_id>7</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>36</top_id>
        <top_name>Labeling &amp; Marketing Communications</top_name>
        <desc>(Responsible Advertising, Consumer Information)</desc>
        <cat_id>7</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>37</top_id>
        <top_name>Consumer Privacy</top_name>
        <desc>(Consumer Complaints, Loss of Consumer Data)</desc>
        <cat_id>7</cat_id>
    </issue>
    <issue>
        <top_id>38</top_id>
        <top_name>Animal Testing</top_name>
        <desc>(Humane, Inhumane, Use of Alternatives)</desc>
        <cat_id>7</cat_id>
    </issue>
  <!-- Table links -->
  <!-- Table peer_rating -->
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>1</pr_id>
        <r_id>1</r_id>
        <pr_score>6.8</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>I like this review</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>0000-00-00 00:00:00</pr_ent_dt>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>2</pr_id>
        <r_id>1</r_id>
        <pr_score>2.5</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>I don't like this review</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>0000-00-00 00:00:00</pr_ent_dt>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>3</pr_id>
        <r_id>1</r_id>
        <pr_score>1</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>bad bad bad</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>0000-00-00 00:00:00</pr_ent_dt>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>4</pr_id>
        <r_id>1</r_id>
        <pr_score>1.5</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>also just bad</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>0000-00-00 00:00:00</pr_ent_dt>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>5</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>2.5</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>a boring review</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>0000-00-00 00:00:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>6</pr_id>
        <r_id>1</r_id>
        <pr_score>3.8</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>testtestesetest</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>0000-00-00 00:00:00</pr_ent_dt>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>7</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>2.5</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>a boring review</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>0000-00-00 00:00:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>8</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>2.5</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>a boring review</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>0000-00-00 00:00:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>9</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>2.5</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>a boring review</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2006-01-31 00:00:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>10</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>2.5</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>a boring review</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-05-27 08:47:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>11</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>2.5</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>a boring review</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-05-28 03:19:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>12</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>2.5</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>a boring review</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-05-28 03:19:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>13</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>2.5</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>a boring review</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-05-28 03:31:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>14</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>3</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>this is a great sample, Lisa!</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-06-03 14:22:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>15</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>0</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>terse</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-07-22 11:19:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>16</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>0</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>terse</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-07-22 11:20:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>17</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>0</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>test</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-07-24 17:52:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>18</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>0</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>good review</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-07-29 05:42:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>19</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>0</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>i like this review</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-08-03 09:32:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>20</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>0</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>This is a test peer rating of a test review.  This review has no substance. </pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-08-14 11:00:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>21</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>0</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>Test peer rating #2.</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-08-14 11:03:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>22</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>0</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>this is a terrible review, you included no sources!</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-08-19 06:44:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>23</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>0</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>That test review is awesome.</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-08-21 09:58:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>24</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>0</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>I don't really like this test review quite as much.</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-08-21 10:00:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>25</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>0</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>The more I read this test review, the more I like it.</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-08-21 10:02:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>26</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>0</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>The guy who wrote this review is a jobber.</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-08-21 10:03:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>27</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>0</pr_score>
        <pr_comment>Factual but only deals with one part of the company</pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-09-09 19:40:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>28</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>0</pr_score>
        <pr_comment></pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-09-10 16:01:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>29</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>0</pr_score>
        <pr_comment></pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-10-30 07:31:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
    <peer_rating>
        <pr_id>30</pr_id>
        <r_id>0</r_id>
        <pr_score>0</pr_score>
        <pr_comment></pr_comment>
        <pr_ent_dt>2007-12-18 18:24:00</pr_ent_dt>
        <uname></uname>
    </peer_rating>
  <!-- Table review -->
    <review>
        <r_id>62</r_id>
        <uname>iwohl</uname>
        <r_score>9</r_score>
        <r_comment>I'm not passing judgment on the entirety of Shell's indirect economic impacts.  I actually think your average oil company has pretty negative indirect economic impacts, given the 'Dutch disease' phenomenon in oil-producing nations.

But I want to say this:  Shell decided to stay in New Orleans after Hurricane Katrina, reopening its offices in One Shell Square in February, 2006.  It wasn't clearly in their interest to do this- no one was really certain what the city would look like in a year.  But, given how much of an economic presence they are in the city (e.g. the number of employees who'd return as a direct result of this decision), it was an important sign of faith and commitment to the recovery of New Orleans.

They followed up on this in a number of ways:  they donated $500,000 to address housing needs for police officers; they provided funding for Jazz Fest; and they sponsored three graduate student interns (including myself) to support community rebuilding efforts in the Broadmoor neighborhood.  They were happy to reap some reputation benefits from this, but I think to a greater extent they saw it as in their long-term interest to help restore a healthy, viable city.

Again, this is a small piece of a global economic impact.  But it showed leadership, and it meant a lot to the residents of New Orleans.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>http://www.csdecisions.com/issue/article/41974/shell_reopens_new_orleans_offices.aspx

http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4155/is_20060423/ai_n16414185

</r_sources>
        <co_id>5</co_id>
        <cat_id>1</cat_id>
        <top_id>28</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-09-27 14:25:13</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>10</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>9</r_score>
        <r_comment>In 2005, Unilever partnered with Oxfam to conduct a study of Unilever's &quot;poverty footprint&quot; in Indonesia.  The report analyzed how Unilever's operations in Indonesia were affecting its supply chain and retailers.

The report concluded that Unilever's impact is positive.  More importantly, I commend Unilever for engaging in such a unique and transparent initiative to understand its indirect economic impacts.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>http://www.oxfam.org.uk/what_we_do/issues/livelihoods/unilever_foreox.htm</r_sources>
        <co_id>14</co_id>
        <cat_id>1</cat_id>
        <top_id>28</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-09-26 21:00:16</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>2</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>10</r_score>
        <r_comment>Chevron received a very high score of 100 out of a possible 100 in the latest (2006) Human Rights Campaign Foundation (HRC) “Corporate Equality Index: A Report Card on Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual and Transgender Equality in Corporate America.”  HRC awards points according to 11 specific performance indicators, including but not limited to: language in corporate non-discrimination policies about sexual orientation and gender identity; diversity training in place; and parity in domestic partner benefits.

HRC updates the performance indicators each year with a mind towards establishing rigorous but achievable goals; their vision is that one day all companies will score a perfect 100.  The report does not provide percentile ranking.  I therefore give Chevron a rating of 10 on this Issue (100/10 = 10), recognizing that other aspects to Diversity &amp; Equal Opportunity are not covered in this Review. </r_comment>
        <r_sources>Human Rights Campaign Foundation, &quot;Corporate Equality Index 2006,&quot; cited 9/7/07 from http://www.hrc.org/documents/HRCCorporateEqualityIndex2006.pdf.</r_sources>
        <co_id>2</co_id>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
        <top_id>33</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-09-07 10:13:05</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>1</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>2</r_score>
        <r_comment>Chevron’s subsidiary Texaco intentionally dumped 19 billion gallons of toxic wastewater and accidentally spilled 16 million gallons of crude oil into Ecuador’s Amazonian rainforest between 1972 and 1991, in what may be the worst oil-related environmental disaster in history.  (By comparison, the Exxon Valdez spilled 10.8 million gallons of crude in Alaska.)  Chevron is now the subject of an ongoing Ecuadoran class action lawsuit involving 30,000 plaintiffs, allegations of fraud brought by the Ecuadoran government, and investigation by the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission for failure to disclose related liabilities to shareholders.  

Texaco is not exclusively responsible for the disaster; Ecuador’s national oil company – PetroEcuador – owned a majority stake in the project, though Texaco maintained full control of the oil consortium’s operations.  PetroEcuador and the Ecuadoran government have failed to hold themselves and Texaco accountable, but this does not excuse Texaco.  Chevron did not own Texaco at the time of the dumping and spills; the two companies merged in 2001 to become ChevronTexaco and in 2005 streamlined the company name to Chevron.  As Texaco’s current owner, Chevron is fully accountable for Texaco’s liabilities.

Chevron’s behavior is concerning for several reasons:

* The sheer scope of the disaster and its long-term impact on the biodiversity of the rainforest and the health and livelihood of local indigenous groups.    

* Texaco intentionally dumped its toxic wastewaters into open, unlined pits, waterways and wetlands despite standard industry practices (in the U.S.) to re-inject such wastewaters deeper underground. 

* Texaco was aware of its spills as they occurred over time.  The company’s response was to simply shut off the flow of petroleum to the damaged pipeline, allow remaining oil in the pipeline to spill out, and then make necessary repairs.  Texaco did not undergo any remediation until lawsuits were brought against the company.  

* Texaco clearly broke international law and Ecuadoran law in the process, as recorded in detail in Judith Kimerling’s article, “The Environmental Audit of Texaco’s Amazon Oil Fields: Environmental Justice or Business as Usual?”, published in Harvard Human Rights Journal in 1994. 

* The formal accountability mechanism for this disaster – developed by Texaco, PetroEcuador and the Ecuadoran government in the early 1990’s – was deeply flawed.  In a 2006 press release, the company says this mechanism was an “exhaustive and transparent negotiation process…” involving “two independent environmental audits.”  But Kimerling demonstrated in 1994 that the audit was neither transparent, exhaustive nor independent: indigenous groups were not consulted; the audit was restricted in scope and time range; and the Ecuadoran government had a clear interest in limiting liability for the consortium, as PetroEcuador was a national oil company.  Moreover, the audit did not account for social, cultural and economic impacts on local communities.  

* Chevron’s remediation efforts are, at best, dramatically insufficient.  The company’s claims have outraged environmental experts and human rights advocates, resulting in accusations of a cover-up.  In 1998, as a result of the audit and an agreement with the Ecuadoran government, Texaco completed a $40 million “remediation” of 156 of 627 unlined toxic waste pits.  The company simply bulldozed the sites, without removing groundwater toxins, paying compensation to affected communities, or addressing the community’s health concerns.  The company claims to this day that such remediation efforts have absolved it from further accountability.  In 2003, the Wall St Journal reported that Chevron’s full liability for remediation and damages may be as much as $5 billion.  

Chevron’s strategy has been to claim protection under the letter of the law, as its operations and remediation were sanctioned by the Ecuadoran government at the time.  But even if the company were legally protected – and Judith Kimerling makes a persuasive case to the contrary – that would not justify its behavior.  Chevron has violated the spirit of the law through dubious agreements with PetroEcuador and the Ecuadoran government – entities that themselves lack accountability to the indigenous groups and the local environment.  Chevron, PetroEcuador and the Ecuadoran government all share tremendous responsibility for the disaster.  Until Chevron initiates a truly accountable process for remediation, the company is only digging itself deeper into the toxic pit it created.

I give Chevron a rating of 2 on this Issue.  The company has engaged in limited remediation efforts and may be legally protected from further liability.  Moreover, most of the behavior in question occurred decades ago, when norms for corporate social responsibility were weaker than they are today.  But ultimately there is no question that Chevron is partly responsible for a tragic environmental and human rights disaster in Ecuador that still requires remediation.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>Amnesty International. “Chevron (CVX) in the Amazon – Oil Rights or Human Rights? Texaco's Legacy, Chevron's Responsibility.”  Cited 4/4/07 from http://www.amnestyusa.org/Business_and_Human_Rights/Chevron_Corporation/page.do?id=1101670&amp;n1=3&amp;n2=26&amp;n3=1242

Amazon Watch. “Chevron’s Dirty Business in Ecuador: 13 Examples That Expose a Corporate Cover-Up.”  Cited 9/3/07 from www.chevrontoxico.com

Chevron.  “Chevron Responds to Amazon Watch Letter” 5/18/05
http://www.texaco.com/sitelets/ecuador/en/press_releases/2005-05-18_amazonwatch.asp

Chevron.  “Chevron Responds to Allegations of Fraud: &quot;Absolutely No Merit”  7/22/06
http://www.texaco.com/sitelets/ecuador/en/press_releases/2006-07-22_allegations.asp

Harvard Human Rights Journal, Vol. 17.  Kimerling, Judith.  “The Environmental Audit of Texaco’s Amazon Oil Fields: Environmental Justice of Business as Usual?”  1994.

International Journal of Epidemiology.  Hurtig, A.K. and M. San Sebastian.  “Epidemiology vs. Epidemiology: The Case of Oil Exploitation in the Amazon Basin of Ecuador.”  8/2/05.

New York Times.  Herbert, Bob.  “Rainforest Jekyll and Hyde?”  10/20/05

Wall St Journal.  “Chevron Would Face $5 Billion Tab For Amazon Cleanup, Expert Says,” 10/30/03.</r_sources>
        <co_id>2</co_id>
        <cat_id>2</cat_id>
        <top_id>16</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-09-05 16:37:10</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>3</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>9</r_score>
        <r_comment>Shell Oil received a relatively high score of 85 out of a possible 100 in the latest (2006) Human Rights Campaign Foundation (HRC) “Corporate Equality Index: A Report Card on Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual and Transgender Equality in Corporate America.”  HRC awards points according to 11 specific performance indicators, including but not limited to: language in corporate non-discrimination policies about sexual orientation and gender identity; diversity training in place; and parity in domestic partner benefits.

HRC updates the performance indicators each year with a mind towards establishing rigorous but achievable goals; their vision is that one day all companies will score a perfect 100.  The report does not provide percentile ranking.  I therefore give Royal Dutch Shell a rating of 9 on this Issue (85/10 = 8.5), recognizing that other aspects to Diversity &amp; Equal Opportunity are not covered in this Review. </r_comment>
        <r_sources>Human Rights Campaign Foundation, &quot;Corporate Equality Index 2006,&quot; cited 9/7/07 from http://www.hrc.org/documents/HRCCorporateEqualityIndex2006.pdf.</r_sources>
        <co_id>5</co_id>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
        <top_id>33</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-09-07 10:13:55</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>4</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>8</r_score>
        <r_comment>ConocoPhillips received a relatively high score of 78 out of a possible 100 in the latest (2006) Human Rights Campaign Foundation (HRC) “Corporate Equality Index: A Report Card on Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual and Transgender Equality in Corporate America.”  HRC awards points according to 11 specific performance indicators, including but not limited to: language in corporate non-discrimination policies about sexual orientation and gender identity; diversity training in place; and parity in domestic partner benefits.

HRC updates the performance indicators each year with a mind towards establishing rigorous but achievable goals; their vision is that one day all companies will score a perfect 100.  The report does not provide percentile ranking.  I therefore give ConocoPhillips a rating of 8 on this Issue (78/10 = 7.8), recognizing that other aspects to Diversity &amp; Equal Opportunity are not covered in this Review. </r_comment>
        <r_sources>Human Rights Campaign Foundation, &quot;Corporate Equality Index 2006,&quot; cited 9/7/07 from http://www.hrc.org/documents/HRCCorporateEqualityIndex2006.pdf.</r_sources>
        <co_id>3</co_id>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
        <top_id>33</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-09-07 10:14:44</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>5</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>10</r_score>
        <r_comment>BP’s U.S. operations, BP America, received a very high score of 100 out of a possible 100 in the latest (2006) Human Rights Campaign Foundation (HRC) “Corporate Equality Index: A Report Card on Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual and Transgender Equality in Corporate America.”  HRC awards points according to 11 specific performance indicators, including but not limited to: language in corporate non-discrimination policies about sexual orientation and gender identity; diversity training in place; and parity in domestic partner benefits.

HRC updates the performance indicators each year with a mind towards establishing rigorous but achievable goals; their vision is that one day all companies will score a perfect 100.  The report does not provide percentile ranking.  I therefore give BP a rating of 10 on this Issue (100/10 = 10), recognizing that other aspects to Diversity &amp; Equal Opportunity are not covered in this Review. </r_comment>
        <r_sources>Human Rights Campaign Foundation, &quot;Corporate Equality Index 2006,&quot; cited 9/7/07 from http://www.hrc.org/documents/HRCCorporateEqualityIndex2006.pdf.</r_sources>
        <co_id>1</co_id>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
        <top_id>33</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-09-07 10:15:36</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>6</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>0</r_score>
        <r_comment>ExxonMobil received a very low score of 0 out of a possible 100 in the latest (2006) Human Rights Campaign Foundation (HRC) “Corporate Equality Index: A Report Card on Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual and Transgender Equality in Corporate America.”  HRC awards points according to 11 specific performance indicators, including but not limited to: language in corporate non-discrimination policies about sexual orientation and gender identity; diversity training in place; and parity in domestic partner benefits.

HRC’s comments on ExxonMobil’s low performance are worth quoting at length:  “ExxonMobil has the dubious distinction of being the only U.S. company to have rolled back both benefits eligibility for its employees’ domestic partners and a non-discrimination policy inclusive of sexual orientation.  When Exxon purchased Mobil in 1999, Mobil had specifically included sexual orientation in its non-discrimination policy and offered benefits to domestic partners.  Exxon did neither.  Mobil’s employees lost the protections and the domestic partner benefits program was closed to new applicants when they were brought under Exxon’s policies.  Since then, the company has consistently refused to add sexual orientation to its non-discrimination policy despite shareholder attempts.  Instead of modifying its written policy for its employees, the company simply professes to its shareholders that it does not discriminate.”

Other leading oil companies – including BP, Chevron, ConocoPhillips, and Shell – scored between 75-100 in the report.

HRC updates the performance indicators each year with a mind towards establishing rigorous but achievable goals; their vision is that one day all companies will score a perfect 100.  The report does not provide percentile ranking.  I therefore give ExxonMobil a rating of 0 on this Issue (0/10 = 0), recognizing that other aspects to Diversity &amp; Equal Opportunity are not covered in this Review. </r_comment>
        <r_sources>Human Rights Campaign Foundation, &quot;Corporate Equality Index 2006,&quot; cited 9/7/07 from http://www.hrc.org/documents/HRCCorporateEqualityIndex2006.pdf.</r_sources>
        <co_id>4</co_id>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
        <top_id>33</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-09-07 10:23:25</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>7</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>8</r_score>
        <r_comment>Colgate-Palmolive received a relatively high score of 78 out of a possible 100 in the latest (2006) Human Rights Campaign Foundation (HRC) “Corporate Equality Index: A Report Card on Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual and Transgender Equality in Corporate America.”  HRC awards points according to 11 specific performance indicators, including but not limited to: language in corporate non-discrimination policies about sexual orientation and gender identity; diversity training in place; and parity in domestic partner benefits.

HRC updates the performance indicators each year with a mind towards establishing rigorous but achievable goals; their vision is that one day all companies will score a perfect 100.  The report does not provide percentile ranking.  I therefore give Colgate-Palmolive a rating of 8 on this Issue (78/10 = 7.8), recognizing that other aspects to Diversity &amp; Equal Opportunity that are not covered in this Review. </r_comment>
        <r_sources>Human Rights Campaign Foundation, &quot;Corporate Equality Index 2006,&quot; cited 9/7/07 from http://www.hrc.org/documents/HRCCorporateEqualityIndex2006.pdf.</r_sources>
        <co_id>8</co_id>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
        <top_id>33</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-09-10 10:40:17</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>8</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>7</r_score>
        <r_comment>Procter &amp; Gamble received a mediocre score of 65 out of a possible 100 in the latest (2006) Human Rights Campaign Foundation (HRC) “Corporate Equality Index: A Report Card on Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual and Transgender Equality in Corporate America.”  HRC awards points according to 11 specific performance indicators, including but not limited to: language in corporate non-discrimination policies about sexual orientation and gender identity; diversity training in place; and parity in domestic partner benefits.

HRC updates the performance indicators each year with a mind towards establishing rigorous but achievable goals; their vision is that one day all companies will score a perfect 100.  The report does not provide percentile ranking.  I therefore give Procter &amp; Gamble a rating of 7 on this Issue (65/10 = 6.5), recognizing that other aspects to Diversity &amp; Equal Opportunity are not covered in this Review. </r_comment>
        <r_sources>Human Rights Campaign Foundation, &quot;Corporate Equality Index 2006,&quot; cited 9/7/07 from http://www.hrc.org/documents/HRCCorporateEqualityIndex2006.pdf.</r_sources>
        <co_id>12</co_id>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
        <top_id>33</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-09-10 10:41:36</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>9</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>9</r_score>
        <r_comment>Kimberly-Clark received a relatively high score of 85 out of a possible 100 in the latest (2006) Human Rights Campaign Foundation (HRC) “Corporate Equality Index: A Report Card on Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual and Transgender Equality in Corporate America.”  HRC awards points according to 11 specific performance indicators, including but not limited to: language in corporate non-discrimination policies about sexual orientation and gender identity; diversity training in place; and parity in domestic partner benefits.

HRC updates the performance indicators each year with a mind towards establishing rigorous but achievable goals; their vision is that one day all companies will score a perfect 100.  The report does not provide percentile ranking.  I therefore give Kimberly-Clark a rating of 9 on this Issue (85/10 = 8.5), recognizing that other aspects to Diversity &amp; Equal Opportunity are not covered in this Review. </r_comment>
        <r_sources>Human Rights Campaign Foundation, &quot;Corporate Equality Index 2006,&quot; cited 9/7/07 from http://www.hrc.org/documents/HRCCorporateEqualityIndex2006.pdf.</r_sources>
        <co_id>10</co_id>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
        <top_id>33</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-09-10 10:42:14</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>72</r_id>
        <uname>dmagida</uname>
        <r_score>0</r_score>
        <r_comment>On Oct 23, 2007 BP &quot;agreed to pay $303 million to settle civil charges and avoid criminal prosecution in the U.S. for allegedly manipulating and cornering the propane market in 2004.&quot; The settlement was between BP and the CFTC and Justice Department. &quot;The CFTC is expected to announce a new civil case tomorrow against an individual BP gasoline trader for alleged wrongdoing in that market.&quot;</r_comment>
        <r_sources>Wall Street Journal 10/24/07</r_sources>
        <co_id>1</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>20</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-24 10:03:24</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>63</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>2</r_score>
        <r_comment>This review is part of a series of reviews that I am submitting about various companies’ lobbying expenditures, using data from The Center for Public Integrity’s “Lobby Watch” program.  I begin with an assessment of an individual company’s performance.  I then specify the criteria I used for this series, and I show comparative scores for industry peers.  I conclude each review with a detailed discussion of the challenges and weaknesses to my approach.

Chevron has a poor record with respect to how much it spends on lobbying the U.S. federal government.  According to The Center for Public Integrity, Chevron spent $5,220,000 on federal lobbying in 2004, more than any of its industry peers except ExxonMobil.  (2004 is the latest year for which data is available.)  

After some contemplation, I decided to use simple criteria for converting a company’s lobbying expenditures to a 0-10 score: the less a company spends, the higher its score.  According to my criteria, Chevron deserves a score of 2.  
  
CRITERIA
Lobbying = $0.  Score = 10
Lobbying &lt;= $100,000.  Score = 9
Lobbying &lt;= $250,000.  Score = 8
Lobbying &lt;= $500,000.  Score = 7
Lobbying &lt;= $750,000.  Score = 6
Lobbying &lt;= $1,000,000.  Score = 5
Lobbying &lt;= $2,500,000.  Score = 4
Lobbying &lt;= $5,000,000.  Score = 3
Lobbying &lt;= $7,500,000.  Score = 2
Lobbying &lt;= $10,000,000.  Score = 1
Lobbying &gt; $10,000,000.  Score = 0

PERFORMANCE OF INDUSTRY PEERS
Total: $80,000.  Score: 9
Shell Oil: $1,020,320.  Score: 4
BP: $2,281,000.  Score: 3
Conoco Phillips: $2,670,438.  Score: 3
ChevronTexaco: $5,220,000.  Score: 2
ExxonMobil: $7,700,000.  Score: 1

There are three flaws in my analysis:

The first flaw: The Center for Public Integrity’s most recent data is from 2004.  I would have preferred to use 2006 data.  As far as I can gather, this delay is due to the process of reporting by the company, collection by the Senate oversight body, and publication by The Center for Public Integrity.

The second flaw: My analysis is limited to corporate lobbying expenditures on the federal government of the USA.  So corporate spending on political campaigns and local or state governments are not included.  I am not aware of any data on local and state governments, though some data may be available for political campaigns through organizations such as the now-defunct BuyBlue.org.  

My analysis does not address corporate lobbying expenditures in other countries.  The USA requires corporations to disclose lobbying expenditures, so data is available from NGOs like The Center for Public Integrity.  [The U.S. Congress should be commended for its leadership on this issue.]  The European Union, regrettably, does not require such disclosure.  I have not searched for data in other countries.  The result is that my analysis is probably unfair to American corporations, which would naturally spend more money lobbying the U.S. government than their European counterparts.  For example, the American household products company Procter &amp; Gamble spends much more on U.S. federal lobbying than its Anglo-Dutch rival Unilever (through Unilever United States, Inc.), but it may well be that Unilever spends more than Procter &amp; Gamble in lobbying the European Union.  

I experimented with setting lower criteria for foreign companies, but that criteria seemed even more arbitrary than the existing criteria: Should foreign companies spend one half of what their American industry peers spend on U.S. federal lobbying?  One third?  One tenth?  Things get even more complicated when we consider whether “Unilever United States, Inc.” and “BP America” should be considered American or foreign.  I finally gave up and decided to use a single set of criteria.  I believe the solution is to add more reviews to this database about corporate lobbying of non-USA governments.  I encourage anyone who is up for the challenge!   

The third flaw: Companies are judged according to absolute dollars spent on lobbying, without any regard to industry norms or company size.  Ignoring industry norms is not really a problem for our purposes, because consumers are usually interested in the marginal difference in performance of industry peers.  The question for the consumer is Exxon vs. Shell, not Exxon vs. Kraft.  [Setting aside the important question of gas vs. hybrid electric.]  So we should not be concerned if certain industries (e.g., oil, pharma, banking) tend to get lower lobbying scores for high lobbying expenditures; consumers will simply be interested in who is comparatively better or worse within those industries.  

Ignoring company size, on the other hand, is problematic.  One might plausibly argue that large companies are entitled to spend more on lobbying in order to defend broader interests with larger impacts on public life.  I experimented with criteria that accounts for company size by measuring the proportion of lobbying expenditures to annual revenues.  The exercise was enlightening.  ExxonMobil, for example, spent $7.7 million on U.S. federal lobbying in 2004, which was no surprise to me.  But I was surprised to learn that ExxonMobil’s lobbying expenditures that year amounted to only a tiny fraction of 1% of its annual revenues of $270 billion.  Put another way, ExxonMobil spent $28.40 on federal lobbying for each $1 million in revenue in the year 2004.  I was stunned at how small this fraction is for ExxonMobil and other major corporations I reviewed.  I was even more surprised at the ratio for a much smaller agribusiness corporation, Cargill, with $460,000 in lobbying expenditures and $230 million in annual revenues in 2004.  For Cargill, the math works out to $2,000 on federal lobbying per $1 million in revenue, more than 70 times the proportion that ExxonMobil spends!  

So the question is, how do we define “high performance” in terms of lobbying expenditures?  Should we reward companies that spend less?  Or reward companies that spend less, relative to their budget?  The advantage of measuring proportions is that it creates a smoother, incremental incentive for any company – large or small – to reduce their lobbying expenditures.  The disadvantage, however, is that the proportions will swing wildly with changes in the company’s reported revenues, reducing the incentive to pay attention to lobbying expenditures.  Moreover, the real-world effect of lobbying dollars is absolute; ExxonMobil’s $7.7 million will have a much greater effect than Cargill’s $460,000 on our governance and politics.  I therefore rejected the proportional criteria in favor of measuring simple, absolute lobbying expenditures, with the recognition that large corporations will tend to get lower scores.

I encourage anyone interested in this issue to improve upon this methodology so that we can develop a robust analysis and fair scoring for corporate lobbying expenditures.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>The Center for Public Integrity. 
http://www.publicintegrity.org/lobby/profile.aspx?act=industries&amp;year=2003&amp;in=74&amp;sub=1 

Fortune Global 500.
http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/global500/2005/index.html</r_sources>
        <co_id>2</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>19</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-17 10:53:59</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>64</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>3</r_score>
        <r_comment>This review is part of a series of reviews that I am submitting about various companies’ lobbying expenditures, using data from The Center for Public Integrity’s “Lobby Watch” program.  I begin with an assessment of an individual company’s performance.  I then specify the criteria I used for this series, and I show comparative scores for industry peers.  I conclude each review with a detailed discussion of the challenges and weaknesses to my approach.

Procter &amp; Gamble has a very poor record with respect to how much it spends on lobbying the U.S. federal government.  According to The Center for Public Integrity, Procter &amp; Gamble spent $2,794,278 on federal lobbying in 2004, much more than its industry peers.  (2004 is the latest year for which data is available.)  

After some contemplation, I decided to use simple criteria for converting a company’s lobbying expenditures to a 0-10 score: the less a company spends, the higher its score.  According to my criteria, Procter &amp; Gamble deserves a score of 3.  

CRITERIA
Lobbying = $0.  Score = 10
Lobbying &lt;= $100,000.  Score = 9
Lobbying &lt;= $250,000.  Score = 8
Lobbying &lt;= $500,000.  Score = 7
Lobbying &lt;= $750,000.  Score = 6
Lobbying &lt;= $1,000,000.  Score = 5
Lobbying &lt;= $2,500,000.  Score = 4
Lobbying &lt;= $5,000,000.  Score = 3
Lobbying &lt;= $7,500,000.  Score = 2
Lobbying &lt;= $10,000,000.  Score = 1
Lobbying &gt; $10,000,000.  Score = 0

PERFORMANCE OF INDUSTRY PEERS
The Clorox Company: $0.  Score: 10
Colgate-Palmolive: &lt;$10,000.  Score: 9
Kimberly-Clark: $100,000.  Score: 9
Unilever United States, Inc.: $540,000.  Score: 6
Procter &amp; Gamble: $2,794,278.  Score: 3

There are three flaws in my analysis:

The first flaw: The Center for Public Integrity’s most recent data is from 2004.  I would have preferred to use 2006 data.  As far as I can gather, this delay is due to the process of reporting by the company, collection by the Senate oversight body, and publication by The Center for Public Integrity.

The second flaw: My analysis is limited to corporate lobbying expenditures on the federal government of the USA.  So corporate spending on political campaigns and local or state governments are not included.  I am not aware of any data on local and state governments, though some data may be available for political campaigns through organizations such as the now-defunct BuyBlue.org.  

My analysis does not address corporate lobbying expenditures in other countries.  The USA requires corporations to disclose lobbying expenditures, so data is available from NGOs like The Center for Public Integrity.  [The U.S. Congress should be commended for its leadership on this issue.]  The European Union, regrettably, does not require such disclosure.  I have not searched for data in other countries.  The result is that my analysis is probably unfair to American corporations, which would naturally spend more money lobbying the U.S. government than their European counterparts.  For example, the American household products company Procter &amp; Gamble spends much more on U.S. federal lobbying than its Anglo-Dutch rival Unilever (through Unilever United States, Inc.), but it may well be that Unilever spends more than Procter &amp; Gamble in lobbying the European Union.  

I experimented with setting lower criteria for foreign companies, but that criteria seemed even more arbitrary than the existing criteria: Should foreign companies spend one half of what their American industry peers spend on U.S. federal lobbying?  One third?  One tenth?  Things get even more complicated when we consider whether “Unilever United States, Inc.” and “BP America” should be considered American or foreign.  I finally gave up and decided to use a single set of criteria.  I believe the solution is to add more reviews to this database about corporate lobbying of non-USA governments.  I encourage anyone who is up for the challenge!   

The third flaw: Companies are judged according to absolute dollars spent on lobbying, without any regard to industry norms or company size.  Ignoring industry norms is not really a problem for our purposes, because consumers are usually interested in the marginal difference in performance of industry peers.  The question for the consumer is Exxon vs. Shell, not Exxon vs. Kraft.  [Setting aside the important question of gas vs. hybrid electric.]  So we should not be concerned if certain industries (e.g., oil, pharma, banking) tend to get lower lobbying scores for high lobbying expenditures; consumers will simply be interested in who is comparatively better or worse within those industries.  

Ignoring company size, on the other hand, is problematic.  One might plausibly argue that large companies are entitled to spend more on lobbying in order to defend broader interests with larger impacts on public life.  I experimented with criteria that accounts for company size by measuring the proportion of lobbying expenditures to annual revenues.  The exercise was enlightening.  ExxonMobil, for example, spent $7.7 million on U.S. federal lobbying in 2004, which was no surprise to me.  But I was surprised to learn that ExxonMobil’s lobbying expenditures that year amounted to only a tiny fraction of 1% of its annual revenues of $270 billion.  Put another way, ExxonMobil spent $28.40 on federal lobbying for each $1 million in revenue in the year 2004.  I was stunned at how small this fraction is for ExxonMobil and other major corporations I reviewed.  I was even more surprised at the ratio for a much smaller agribusiness corporation, Cargill, with $460,000 in lobbying expenditures and $230 million in annual revenues in 2004.  For Cargill, the math works out to $2,000 on federal lobbying per $1 million in revenue, more than 70 times the proportion that ExxonMobil spends!  

So the question is, how do we define “high performance” in terms of lobbying expenditures?  Should we reward companies that spend less?  Or reward companies that spend less, relative to their budget?  The advantage of measuring proportions is that it creates a smoother, incremental incentive for any company – large or small – to reduce their lobbying expenditures.  The disadvantage, however, is that the proportions will swing wildly with changes in the company’s reported revenues, reducing the incentive to pay attention to lobbying expenditures.  Moreover, the real-world effect of lobbying dollars is absolute; ExxonMobil’s $7.7 million will have a much greater effect than Cargill’s $460,000 on our governance and politics.  I therefore rejected the proportional criteria in favor of measuring simple, absolute lobbying expenditures, with the recognition that large corporations will tend to get lower scores.

I encourage anyone interested in this issue to improve upon this methodology so that we can develop a robust analysis and fair scoring for corporate lobbying expenditures.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>The Center for Public Integrity
http://www.publicintegrity.org/lobby/profile.aspx?act=industries&amp;year=2003&amp;in=74&amp;sub=1

Fortune Global 500.
http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/global500/2005/index.html</r_sources>
        <co_id>12</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>19</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-17 10:57:29</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>65</r_id>
        <uname>dmagida</uname>
        <r_score>10</r_score>
        <r_comment>while this comment does not address corporate wide conservation, P&amp;G deserves commendaton for leading the way in dramatically reducing the amount of packaging in some of its consumer products- specifically laundry detergent and fabric softener. P&amp;G has reformulated its product ingredients and manufacturing process so as to offer super concentrated liquids. These, in turn, require 1/3 the regular amount of packaging. With over half the market, these steps will have a major positive impact on resource conservation. </r_comment>
        <r_sources>Wall St. Journal (approx date early September 2007)</r_sources>
        <co_id>12</co_id>
        <cat_id>2</cat_id>
        <top_id>15</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-21 08:26:41</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>66</r_id>
        <uname>dmagida</uname>
        <r_score>9</r_score>
        <r_comment>while I can't rate P&amp;G on corporate-wide public policies, it deserves commendation for its philanthropic program of donating millions of dollars worth of free consumer water filtration systems in third world, severely impoverished countries. </r_comment>
        <r_sources>Proctor and Gamble annual report</r_sources>
        <co_id>12</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>19</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-21 08:36:29</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>67</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>3</r_score>
        <r_comment>This review is part of a series of reviews that I am submitting about various companies’ lobbying expenditures, using data from The Center for Public Integrity’s “Lobby Watch” program.  I begin with an assessment of an individual company’s performance.  I then specify the criteria I used for this series, and I show comparative scores for industry peers.  I conclude each review with a detailed discussion of the challenges and weaknesses to my approach.

BP has a relatively poor record with respect to how much it spends on lobbying the U.S. federal government.  According to The Center for Public Integrity, BP spent $2,281,000 on federal lobbying in 2004, more than than any other non-U.S. oil company.  (2004 is the latest year for which data is available.)  

After some contemplation, I decided to use simple criteria for converting a company’s lobbying expenditures to a 0-10 score: the less a company spends, the higher its score.  According to my criteria, BP deserves a score of 3.  
  
CRITERIA
Lobbying = $0.  Score = 10
Lobbying &lt;= $100,000.  Score = 9
Lobbying &lt;= $250,000.  Score = 8
Lobbying &lt;= $500,000.  Score = 7
Lobbying &lt;= $750,000.  Score = 6
Lobbying &lt;= $1,000,000.  Score = 5
Lobbying &lt;= $2,500,000.  Score = 4
Lobbying &lt;= $5,000,000.  Score = 3
Lobbying &lt;= $7,500,000.  Score = 2
Lobbying &lt;= $10,000,000.  Score = 1
Lobbying &gt; $10,000,000.  Score = 0

PERFORMANCE OF INDUSTRY PEERS
Total: $80,000.  Score: 9
Shell Oil: $1,020,320.  Score: 4
BP: $2,281,000.  Score: 3
Conoco Phillips: $2,670,438.  Score: 3
ChevronTexaco: $5,220,000.  Score: 2
ExxonMobil: $7,700,000.  Score: 1

There are three flaws in my analysis:

The first flaw: The Center for Public Integrity’s most recent data is from 2004.  I would have preferred to use 2006 data.  As far as I can gather, this delay is due to the process of reporting by the company, collection by the Senate oversight body, and publication by The Center for Public Integrity.

The second flaw: My analysis is limited to corporate lobbying expenditures on the federal government of the USA.  So corporate spending on political campaigns and local or state governments are not included.  I am not aware of any data on local and state governments, though some data may be available for political campaigns through organizations such as the now-defunct BuyBlue.org.  

My analysis does not address corporate lobbying expenditures in other countries.  The USA requires corporations to disclose lobbying expenditures, so data is available from NGOs like The Center for Public Integrity.  [The U.S. Congress should be commended for its leadership on this issue.]  The European Union, regrettably, does not require such disclosure.  I have not searched for data in other countries.  The result is that my analysis is probably unfair to American corporations, which would naturally spend more money lobbying the U.S. government than their European counterparts.  For example, the American household products company Procter &amp; Gamble spends much more on U.S. federal lobbying than its Anglo-Dutch rival Unilever (through Unilever United States, Inc.), but it may well be that Unilever spends more than Procter &amp; Gamble in lobbying the European Union.  

I experimented with setting lower criteria for foreign companies, but that criteria seemed even more arbitrary than the existing criteria: Should foreign companies spend one half of what their American industry peers spend on U.S. federal lobbying?  One third?  One tenth?  Things get even more complicated when we consider whether “Unilever United States, Inc.” and “BP America” should be considered American or foreign.  I finally gave up and decided to use a single set of criteria.  I believe the solution is to add more reviews to this database about corporate lobbying of non-USA governments.  I encourage anyone who is up for the challenge!   

The third flaw: Companies are judged according to absolute dollars spent on lobbying, without any regard to industry norms or company size.  Ignoring industry norms is not really a problem for our purposes, because consumers are usually interested in the marginal difference in performance of industry peers.  The question for the consumer is Exxon vs. Shell, not Exxon vs. Kraft.  [Setting aside the important question of gas vs. hybrid electric.]  So we should not be concerned if certain industries (e.g., oil, pharma, banking) tend to get lower lobbying scores for high lobbying expenditures; consumers will simply be interested in who is comparatively better or worse within those industries.  

Ignoring company size, on the other hand, is problematic.  One might plausibly argue that large companies are entitled to spend more on lobbying in order to defend broader interests with larger impacts on public life.  I experimented with criteria that accounts for company size by measuring the proportion of lobbying expenditures to annual revenues.  The exercise was enlightening.  ExxonMobil, for example, spent $7.7 million on U.S. federal lobbying in 2004, which was no surprise to me.  But I was surprised to learn that ExxonMobil’s lobbying expenditures that year amounted to only a tiny fraction of 1% of its annual revenues of $270 billion.  Put another way, ExxonMobil spent $28.40 on federal lobbying for each $1 million in revenue in the year 2004.  I was stunned at how small this fraction is for ExxonMobil and other major corporations I reviewed.  I was even more surprised at the ratio for a much smaller agribusiness corporation, Cargill, with $460,000 in lobbying expenditures and $230 million in annual revenues in 2004.  For Cargill, the math works out to $2,000 on federal lobbying per $1 million in revenue, more than 70 times the proportion that ExxonMobil spends!  

So the question is, how do we define “high performance” in terms of lobbying expenditures?  Should we reward companies that spend less?  Or reward companies that spend less, relative to their budget?  The advantage of measuring proportions is that it creates a smoother, incremental incentive for any company – large or small – to reduce their lobbying expenditures.  The disadvantage, however, is that the proportions will swing wildly with changes in the company’s reported revenues, reducing the incentive to pay attention to lobbying expenditures.  Moreover, the real-world effect of lobbying dollars is absolute; ExxonMobil’s $7.7 million will have a much greater effect than Cargill’s $460,000 on our governance and politics.  I therefore rejected the proportional criteria in favor of measuring simple, absolute lobbying expenditures, with the recognition that large corporations will tend to get lower scores.

I encourage anyone interested in this issue to improve upon this methodology so that we can develop a robust analysis and fair scoring for corporate lobbying expenditures.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>The Center for Public Integrity
http://www.publicintegrity.org/lobby/profile.aspx?act=industries&amp;year=2003&amp;in=74&amp;sub=1

Fortune Global 500.
http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/global500/2005/index.html</r_sources>
        <co_id>1</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>19</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-22 11:01:04</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>68</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>3</r_score>
        <r_comment>This review is part of a series of reviews that I am submitting about various companies’ lobbying expenditures, using data from The Center for Public Integrity’s “Lobby Watch” program.  I begin with an assessment of an individual company’s performance.  I then specify the criteria I used for this series, and I show comparative scores for industry peers.  I conclude each review with a detailed discussion of the challenges and weaknesses to my approach.

ConocoPhillips has a relatively poor record with respect to how much it spends on lobbying the U.S. federal government.  According to The Center for Public Integrity, ConocoPhillips spent $2,670,438 on federal lobbying in 2004, which is more than most of its industry peers but less than some other American oil companies.  (2004 is the latest year for which data is available.)  

After some contemplation, I decided to use simple criteria for converting a company’s lobbying expenditures to a 0-10 score: the less a company spends, the higher its score.  According to my criteria, ConocoPhillips deserves a score of 3.  
  
CRITERIA
Lobbying = $0.  Score = 10
Lobbying &lt;= $100,000.  Score = 9
Lobbying &lt;= $250,000.  Score = 8
Lobbying &lt;= $500,000.  Score = 7
Lobbying &lt;= $750,000.  Score = 6
Lobbying &lt;= $1,000,000.  Score = 5
Lobbying &lt;= $2,500,000.  Score = 4
Lobbying &lt;= $5,000,000.  Score = 3
Lobbying &lt;= $7,500,000.  Score = 2
Lobbying &lt;= $10,000,000.  Score = 1
Lobbying &gt; $10,000,000.  Score = 0

PERFORMANCE OF INDUSTRY PEERS
Total: $80,000.  Score: 9
Shell Oil: $1,020,320.  Score: 4
BP: $2,281,000.  Score: 3
Conoco Phillips: $2,670,438.  Score: 3
ChevronTexaco: $5,220,000.  Score: 2
ExxonMobil: $7,700,000.  Score: 1

There are three flaws in my analysis:

The first flaw: The Center for Public Integrity’s most recent data is from 2004.  I would have preferred to use 2006 data.  As far as I can gather, this delay is due to the process of reporting by the company, collection by the Senate oversight body, and publication by The Center for Public Integrity.

The second flaw: My analysis is limited to corporate lobbying expenditures on the federal government of the USA.  So corporate spending on political campaigns and local or state governments are not included.  I am not aware of any data on local and state governments, though some data may be available for political campaigns through organizations such as the now-defunct BuyBlue.org.  

My analysis does not address corporate lobbying expenditures in other countries.  The USA requires corporations to disclose lobbying expenditures, so data is available from NGOs like The Center for Public Integrity.  [The U.S. Congress should be commended for its leadership on this issue.]  The European Union, regrettably, does not require such disclosure.  I have not searched for data in other countries.  The result is that my analysis is probably unfair to American corporations, which would naturally spend more money lobbying the U.S. government than their European counterparts.  For example, the American household products company Procter &amp; Gamble spends much more on U.S. federal lobbying than its Anglo-Dutch rival Unilever (through Unilever United States, Inc.), but it may well be that Unilever spends more than Procter &amp; Gamble in lobbying the European Union.  

I experimented with setting lower criteria for foreign companies, but that criteria seemed even more arbitrary than the existing criteria: Should foreign companies spend one half of what their American industry peers spend on U.S. federal lobbying?  One third?  One tenth?  Things get even more complicated when we consider whether “Unilever United States, Inc.” and “BP America” should be considered American or foreign.  I finally gave up and decided to use a single set of criteria.  I believe the solution is to add more reviews to this database about corporate lobbying of non-USA governments.  I encourage anyone who is up for the challenge!   

The third flaw: Companies are judged according to absolute dollars spent on lobbying, without any regard to industry norms or company size.  Ignoring industry norms is not really a problem for our purposes, because consumers are usually interested in the marginal difference in performance of industry peers.  The question for the consumer is Exxon vs. Shell, not Exxon vs. Kraft.  [Setting aside the important question of gas vs. hybrid electric.]  So we should not be concerned if certain industries (e.g., oil, pharma, banking) tend to get lower lobbying scores for high lobbying expenditures; consumers will simply be interested in who is comparatively better or worse within those industries.  

Ignoring company size, on the other hand, is problematic.  One might plausibly argue that large companies are entitled to spend more on lobbying in order to defend broader interests with larger impacts on public life.  I experimented with criteria that accounts for company size by measuring the proportion of lobbying expenditures to annual revenues.  The exercise was enlightening.  ExxonMobil, for example, spent $7.7 million on U.S. federal lobbying in 2004, which was no surprise to me.  But I was surprised to learn that ExxonMobil’s lobbying expenditures that year amounted to only a tiny fraction of 1% of its annual revenues of $270 billion.  Put another way, ExxonMobil spent $28.40 on federal lobbying for each $1 million in revenue in the year 2004.  I was stunned at how small this fraction is for ExxonMobil and other major corporations I reviewed.  I was even more surprised at the ratio for a much smaller agribusiness corporation, Cargill, with $460,000 in lobbying expenditures and $230 million in annual revenues in 2004.  For Cargill, the math works out to $2,000 on federal lobbying per $1 million in revenue, more than 70 times the proportion that ExxonMobil spends!  

So the question is, how do we define “high performance” in terms of lobbying expenditures?  Should we reward companies that spend less?  Or reward companies that spend less, relative to their budget?  The advantage of measuring proportions is that it creates a smoother, incremental incentive for any company – large or small – to reduce their lobbying expenditures.  The disadvantage, however, is that the proportions will swing wildly with changes in the company’s reported revenues, reducing the incentive to pay attention to lobbying expenditures.  Moreover, the real-world effect of lobbying dollars is absolute; ExxonMobil’s $7.7 million will have a much greater effect than Cargill’s $460,000 on our governance and politics.  I therefore rejected the proportional criteria in favor of measuring simple, absolute lobbying expenditures, with the recognition that large corporations will tend to get lower scores.

I encourage anyone interested in this issue to improve upon this methodology so that we can develop a robust analysis and fair scoring for corporate lobbying expenditures.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>The Center for Public Integrity
http://www.publicintegrity.org/lobby/profile.aspx?act=industries&amp;year=2003&amp;in=74&amp;sub=1

Fortune Global 500.
http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/global500/2005/index.html</r_sources>
        <co_id>3</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>19</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-22 11:05:52</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>69</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>4</r_score>
        <r_comment>This review is part of a series of reviews that I am submitting about various companies’ lobbying expenditures, using data from The Center for Public Integrity’s “Lobby Watch” program.  I begin with an assessment of an individual company’s performance.  I then specify the criteria I used for this series, and I show comparative scores for industry peers.  I conclude each review with a detailed discussion of the challenges and weaknesses to my approach.

Shell has a mediocre record with respect to how much it spends on lobbying the U.S. federal government.  According to The Center for Public Integrity, Shell spent $1,020,320 on federal lobbying in 2004.  (2004 is the latest year for which data is available.)  

After some contemplation, I decided to use simple criteria for converting a company’s lobbying expenditures to a 0-10 score: the less a company spends, the higher its score.  According to my criteria, Shell deserves a score of 4.  
  
CRITERIA
Lobbying = $0.  Score = 10
Lobbying &lt;= $100,000.  Score = 9
Lobbying &lt;= $250,000.  Score = 8
Lobbying &lt;= $500,000.  Score = 7
Lobbying &lt;= $750,000.  Score = 6
Lobbying &lt;= $1,000,000.  Score = 5
Lobbying &lt;= $2,500,000.  Score = 4
Lobbying &lt;= $5,000,000.  Score = 3
Lobbying &lt;= $7,500,000.  Score = 2
Lobbying &lt;= $10,000,000.  Score = 1
Lobbying &gt; $10,000,000.  Score = 0

PERFORMANCE OF INDUSTRY PEERS
Total: $80,000.  Score: 9
Shell Oil: $1,020,320.  Score: 4
BP: $2,281,000.  Score: 3
Conoco Phillips: $2,670,438.  Score: 3
ChevronTexaco: $5,220,000.  Score: 2
ExxonMobil: $7,700,000.  Score: 1

There are three flaws in my analysis:

The first flaw: The Center for Public Integrity’s most recent data is from 2004.  I would have preferred to use 2006 data.  As far as I can gather, this delay is due to the process of reporting by the company, collection by the Senate oversight body, and publication by The Center for Public Integrity.

The second flaw: My analysis is limited to corporate lobbying expenditures on the federal government of the USA.  So corporate spending on political campaigns and local or state governments are not included.  I am not aware of any data on local and state governments, though some data may be available for political campaigns through organizations such as the now-defunct BuyBlue.org.  

My analysis does not address corporate lobbying expenditures in other countries.  The USA requires corporations to disclose lobbying expenditures, so data is available from NGOs like The Center for Public Integrity.  [The U.S. Congress should be commended for its leadership on this issue.]  The European Union, regrettably, does not require such disclosure.  I have not searched for data in other countries.  The result is that my analysis is probably unfair to American corporations, which would naturally spend more money lobbying the U.S. government than their European counterparts.  For example, the American household products company Procter &amp; Gamble spends much more on U.S. federal lobbying than its Anglo-Dutch rival Unilever (through Unilever United States, Inc.), but it may well be that Unilever spends more than Procter &amp; Gamble in lobbying the European Union.  

I experimented with setting lower criteria for foreign companies, but that criteria seemed even more arbitrary than the existing criteria: Should foreign companies spend one half of what their American industry peers spend on U.S. federal lobbying?  One third?  One tenth?  Things get even more complicated when we consider whether “Unilever United States, Inc.” and “BP America” should be considered American or foreign.  I finally gave up and decided to use a single set of criteria.  I believe the solution is to add more reviews to this database about corporate lobbying of non-USA governments.  I encourage anyone who is up for the challenge!   

The third flaw: Companies are judged according to absolute dollars spent on lobbying, without any regard to industry norms or company size.  Ignoring industry norms is not really a problem for our purposes, because consumers are usually interested in the marginal difference in performance of industry peers.  The question for the consumer is Exxon vs. Shell, not Exxon vs. Kraft.  [Setting aside the important question of gas vs. hybrid electric.]  So we should not be concerned if certain industries (e.g., oil, pharma, banking) tend to get lower lobbying scores for high lobbying expenditures; consumers will simply be interested in who is comparatively better or worse within those industries.  

Ignoring company size, on the other hand, is problematic.  One might plausibly argue that large companies are entitled to spend more on lobbying in order to defend broader interests with larger impacts on public life.  I experimented with criteria that accounts for company size by measuring the proportion of lobbying expenditures to annual revenues.  The exercise was enlightening.  ExxonMobil, for example, spent $7.7 million on U.S. federal lobbying in 2004, which was no surprise to me.  But I was surprised to learn that ExxonMobil’s lobbying expenditures that year amounted to only a tiny fraction of 1% of its annual revenues of $270 billion.  Put another way, ExxonMobil spent $28.40 on federal lobbying for each $1 million in revenue in the year 2004.  I was stunned at how small this fraction is for ExxonMobil and other major corporations I reviewed.  I was even more surprised at the ratio for a much smaller agribusiness corporation, Cargill, with $460,000 in lobbying expenditures and $230 million in annual revenues in 2004.  For Cargill, the math works out to $2,000 on federal lobbying per $1 million in revenue, more than 70 times the proportion that ExxonMobil spends!  

So the question is, how do we define “high performance” in terms of lobbying expenditures?  Should we reward companies that spend less?  Or reward companies that spend less, relative to their budget?  The advantage of measuring proportions is that it creates a smoother, incremental incentive for any company – large or small – to reduce their lobbying expenditures.  The disadvantage, however, is that the proportions will swing wildly with changes in the company’s reported revenues, reducing the incentive to pay attention to lobbying expenditures.  Moreover, the real-world effect of lobbying dollars is absolute; ExxonMobil’s $7.7 million will have a much greater effect than Cargill’s $460,000 on our governance and politics.  I therefore rejected the proportional criteria in favor of measuring simple, absolute lobbying expenditures, with the recognition that large corporations will tend to get lower scores.

I encourage anyone interested in this issue to improve upon this methodology so that we can develop a robust analysis and fair scoring for corporate lobbying expenditures.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>The Center for Public Integrity
http://www.publicintegrity.org/lobby/profile.aspx?act=industries&amp;year=2003&amp;in=74&amp;sub=1

Fortune Global 500.
http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/global500/2005/index.html</r_sources>
        <co_id>5</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>19</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-22 11:08:31</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>70</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>1</r_score>
        <r_comment>This review is part of a series of reviews that I am submitting about various companies’ lobbying expenditures, using data from The Center for Public Integrity’s “Lobby Watch” program.  I begin with an assessment of an individual company’s performance.  I then specify the criteria I used for this series, and I show comparative scores for industry peers.  I conclude each review with a detailed discussion of the challenges and weaknesses to my approach.

ExxonMobil has a very poor record with respect to how much it spends on lobbying the U.S. federal government.  According to The Center for Public Integrity, ExxonMobil spent $7,700,000 on federal lobbying in 2004, more than any of its industry peers.  (2004 is the latest year for which data is available.)  

After some contemplation, I decided to use simple criteria for converting a company’s lobbying expenditures to a 0-10 score: the less a company spends, the higher its score.  According to my criteria, ExxonMobil deserves a score of 1.  
  
CRITERIA
Lobbying = $0.  Score = 10
Lobbying &lt;= $100,000.  Score = 9
Lobbying &lt;= $250,000.  Score = 8
Lobbying &lt;= $500,000.  Score = 7
Lobbying &lt;= $750,000.  Score = 6
Lobbying &lt;= $1,000,000.  Score = 5
Lobbying &lt;= $2,500,000.  Score = 4
Lobbying &lt;= $5,000,000.  Score = 3
Lobbying &lt;= $7,500,000.  Score = 2
Lobbying &lt;= $10,000,000.  Score = 1
Lobbying &gt; $10,000,000.  Score = 0

PERFORMANCE OF INDUSTRY PEERS
Total: $80,000.  Score: 9
Shell Oil: $1,020,320.  Score: 4
BP: $2,281,000.  Score: 3
Conoco Phillips: $2,670,438.  Score: 3
ChevronTexaco: $5,220,000.  Score: 2
ExxonMobil: $7,700,000.  Score: 1

There are three flaws in my analysis:

The first flaw: The Center for Public Integrity’s most recent data is from 2004.  I would have preferred to use 2006 data.  As far as I can gather, this delay is due to the process of reporting by the company, collection by the Senate oversight body, and publication by The Center for Public Integrity.

The second flaw: My analysis is limited to corporate lobbying expenditures on the federal government of the USA.  So corporate spending on political campaigns and local or state governments are not included.  I am not aware of any data on local and state governments, though some data may be available for political campaigns through organizations such as the now-defunct BuyBlue.org.  

My analysis does not address corporate lobbying expenditures in other countries.  The USA requires corporations to disclose lobbying expenditures, so data is available from NGOs like The Center for Public Integrity.  [The U.S. Congress should be commended for its leadership on this issue.]  The European Union, regrettably, does not require such disclosure.  I have not searched for data in other countries.  The result is that my analysis is probably unfair to American corporations, which would naturally spend more money lobbying the U.S. government than their European counterparts.  For example, the American household products company Procter &amp; Gamble spends much more on U.S. federal lobbying than its Anglo-Dutch rival Unilever (through Unilever United States, Inc.), but it may well be that Unilever spends more than Procter &amp; Gamble in lobbying the European Union.  

I experimented with setting lower criteria for foreign companies, but that criteria seemed even more arbitrary than the existing criteria: Should foreign companies spend one half of what their American industry peers spend on U.S. federal lobbying?  One third?  One tenth?  Things get even more complicated when we consider whether “Unilever United States, Inc.” and “BP America” should be considered American or foreign.  I finally gave up and decided to use a single set of criteria.  I believe the solution is to add more reviews to this database about corporate lobbying of non-USA governments.  I encourage anyone who is up for the challenge!   

The third flaw: Companies are judged according to absolute dollars spent on lobbying, without any regard to industry norms or company size.  Ignoring industry norms is not really a problem for our purposes, because consumers are usually interested in the marginal difference in performance of industry peers.  The question for the consumer is Exxon vs. Shell, not Exxon vs. Kraft.  [Setting aside the important question of gas vs. hybrid electric.]  So we should not be concerned if certain industries (e.g., oil, pharma, banking) tend to get lower lobbying scores for high lobbying expenditures; consumers will simply be interested in who is comparatively better or worse within those industries.  

Ignoring company size, on the other hand, is problematic.  One might plausibly argue that large companies are entitled to spend more on lobbying in order to defend broader interests with larger impacts on public life.  I experimented with criteria that accounts for company size by measuring the proportion of lobbying expenditures to annual revenues.  The exercise was enlightening.  ExxonMobil, for example, spent $7.7 million on U.S. federal lobbying in 2004, which was no surprise to me.  But I was surprised to learn that ExxonMobil’s lobbying expenditures that year amounted to only a tiny fraction of 1% of its annual revenues of $270 billion.  Put another way, ExxonMobil spent $28.40 on federal lobbying for each $1 million in revenue in the year 2004.  I was stunned at how small this fraction is for ExxonMobil and other major corporations I reviewed.  I was even more surprised at the ratio for a much smaller agribusiness corporation, Cargill, with $460,000 in lobbying expenditures and $230 million in annual revenues in 2004.  For Cargill, the math works out to $2,000 on federal lobbying per $1 million in revenue, more than 70 times the proportion that ExxonMobil spends!  

So the question is, how do we define “high performance” in terms of lobbying expenditures?  Should we reward companies that spend less?  Or reward companies that spend less, relative to their budget?  The advantage of measuring proportions is that it creates a smoother, incremental incentive for any company – large or small – to reduce their lobbying expenditures.  The disadvantage, however, is that the proportions will swing wildly with changes in the company’s reported revenues, reducing the incentive to pay attention to lobbying expenditures.  Moreover, the real-world effect of lobbying dollars is absolute; ExxonMobil’s $7.7 million will have a much greater effect than Cargill’s $460,000 on our governance and politics.  I therefore rejected the proportional criteria in favor of measuring simple, absolute lobbying expenditures, with the recognition that large corporations will tend to get lower scores.

I encourage anyone interested in this issue to improve upon this methodology so that we can develop a robust analysis and fair scoring for corporate lobbying expenditures.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>The Center for Public Integrity
http://www.publicintegrity.org/lobby/profile.aspx?act=industries&amp;year=2003&amp;in=74&amp;sub=1

Fortune Global 500.
http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/global500/2005/index.html</r_sources>
        <co_id>4</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>19</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-22 11:11:31</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>71</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>9</r_score>
        <r_comment>This review is part of a series of reviews that I am submitting about various companies’ lobbying expenditures, using data from The Center for Public Integrity’s “Lobby Watch” program.  I begin with an assessment of an individual company’s performance.  I then specify the criteria I used for this series, and I show comparative scores for industry peers.  I conclude each review with a detailed discussion of the challenges and weaknesses to my approach.

Total has a relatively good record with respect to how much it spends on lobbying the U.S. federal government.  According to The Center for Public Integrity, Total spent only $80,000 on federal lobbying in 2004, much less than its industry peers.  (2004 is the latest year for which data is available.)  

After some contemplation, I decided to use simple criteria for converting a company’s lobbying expenditures to a 0-10 score: the less a company spends, the higher its score.  According to my criteria, Total deserves a score of 9.  
  
CRITERIA
Lobbying = $0.  Score = 10
Lobbying &lt;= $100,000.  Score = 9
Lobbying &lt;= $250,000.  Score = 8
Lobbying &lt;= $500,000.  Score = 7
Lobbying &lt;= $750,000.  Score = 6
Lobbying &lt;= $1,000,000.  Score = 5
Lobbying &lt;= $2,500,000.  Score = 4
Lobbying &lt;= $5,000,000.  Score = 3
Lobbying &lt;= $7,500,000.  Score = 2
Lobbying &lt;= $10,000,000.  Score = 1
Lobbying &gt; $10,000,000.  Score = 0

PERFORMANCE OF INDUSTRY PEERS
Total: $80,000.  Score: 9
Shell Oil: $1,020,320.  Score: 4
BP: $2,281,000.  Score: 3
Conoco Phillips: $2,670,438.  Score: 3
ChevronTexaco: $5,220,000.  Score: 2
ExxonMobil: $7,700,000.  Score: 1

There are three flaws in my analysis:

The first flaw: The Center for Public Integrity’s most recent data is from 2004.  I would have preferred to use 2006 data.  As far as I can gather, this delay is due to the process of reporting by the company, collection by the Senate oversight body, and publication by The Center for Public Integrity.

The second flaw: My analysis is limited to corporate lobbying expenditures on the federal government of the USA.  So corporate spending on political campaigns and local or state governments are not included.  I am not aware of any data on local and state governments, though some data may be available for political campaigns through organizations such as the now-defunct BuyBlue.org.  

My analysis does not address corporate lobbying expenditures in other countries.  The USA requires corporations to disclose lobbying expenditures, so data is available from NGOs like The Center for Public Integrity.  [The U.S. Congress should be commended for its leadership on this issue.]  The European Union, regrettably, does not require such disclosure.  I have not searched for data in other countries.  The result is that my analysis is probably unfair to American corporations, which would naturally spend more money lobbying the U.S. government than their European counterparts.  For example, the American household products company Procter &amp; Gamble spends much more on U.S. federal lobbying than its Anglo-Dutch rival Unilever (through Unilever United States, Inc.), but it may well be that Unilever spends more than Procter &amp; Gamble in lobbying the European Union.  

I experimented with setting lower criteria for foreign companies, but that criteria seemed even more arbitrary than the existing criteria: Should foreign companies spend one half of what their American industry peers spend on U.S. federal lobbying?  One third?  One tenth?  Things get even more complicated when we consider whether “Unilever United States, Inc.” and “BP America” should be considered American or foreign.  I finally gave up and decided to use a single set of criteria.  I believe the solution is to add more reviews to this database about corporate lobbying of non-USA governments.  I encourage anyone who is up for the challenge!   

The third flaw: Companies are judged according to absolute dollars spent on lobbying, without any regard to industry norms or company size.  Ignoring industry norms is not really a problem for our purposes, because consumers are usually interested in the marginal difference in performance of industry peers.  The question for the consumer is Exxon vs. Shell, not Exxon vs. Kraft.  [Setting aside the important question of gas vs. hybrid electric.]  So we should not be concerned if certain industries (e.g., oil, pharma, banking) tend to get lower lobbying scores for high lobbying expenditures; consumers will simply be interested in who is comparatively better or worse within those industries.  

Ignoring company size, on the other hand, is problematic.  One might plausibly argue that large companies are entitled to spend more on lobbying in order to defend broader interests with larger impacts on public life.  I experimented with criteria that accounts for company size by measuring the proportion of lobbying expenditures to annual revenues.  The exercise was enlightening.  ExxonMobil, for example, spent $7.7 million on U.S. federal lobbying in 2004, which was no surprise to me.  But I was surprised to learn that ExxonMobil’s lobbying expenditures that year amounted to only a tiny fraction of 1% of its annual revenues of $270 billion.  Put another way, ExxonMobil spent $28.40 on federal lobbying for each $1 million in revenue in the year 2004.  I was stunned at how small this fraction is for ExxonMobil and other major corporations I reviewed.  I was even more surprised at the ratio for a much smaller agribusiness corporation, Cargill, with $460,000 in lobbying expenditures and $230 million in annual revenues in 2004.  For Cargill, the math works out to $2,000 on federal lobbying per $1 million in revenue, more than 70 times the proportion that ExxonMobil spends!  

So the question is, how do we define “high performance” in terms of lobbying expenditures?  Should we reward companies that spend less?  Or reward companies that spend less, relative to their budget?  The advantage of measuring proportions is that it creates a smoother, incremental incentive for any company – large or small – to reduce their lobbying expenditures.  The disadvantage, however, is that the proportions will swing wildly with changes in the company’s reported revenues, reducing the incentive to pay attention to lobbying expenditures.  Moreover, the real-world effect of lobbying dollars is absolute; ExxonMobil’s $7.7 million will have a much greater effect than Cargill’s $460,000 on our governance and politics.  I therefore rejected the proportional criteria in favor of measuring simple, absolute lobbying expenditures, with the recognition that large corporations will tend to get lower scores.

I encourage anyone interested in this issue to improve upon this methodology so that we can develop a robust analysis and fair scoring for corporate lobbying expenditures.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>The Center for Public Integrity
http://www.publicintegrity.org/lobby/profile.aspx?act=industries&amp;year=2003&amp;in=74&amp;sub=1

Fortune Global 500.
http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/global500/2005/index.html</r_sources>
        <co_id>7</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>19</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-22 11:13:43</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>73</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>9</r_score>
        <r_comment>This review is part of a series of reviews that I am submitting about various companies’ lobbying expenditures, using data from The Center for Public Integrity’s “Lobby Watch” program.  I begin with an assessment of an individual company’s performance.  I then specify the criteria I used for this series, and I show comparative scores for industry peers.  I conclude each review with a detailed discussion of the challenges and weaknesses to my approach.

Colgate-Palmolive has a relatively good record with respect to how much it spends on lobbying the U.S. federal government.  According to The Center for Public Integrity, Colgate-Palmolive spent less than $10,000 on federal lobbying in 2004, much less than its industry peers.  (2004 is the latest year for which data is available.)  

After some contemplation, I decided to use simple criteria for converting a company’s lobbying expenditures to a 0-10 score: the less a company spends, the higher its score.  According to my criteria, Colgate-Palmolive deserves a score of 9.  

CRITERIA
Lobbying = $0.  Score = 10
Lobbying &lt;= $100,000.  Score = 9
Lobbying &lt;= $250,000.  Score = 8
Lobbying &lt;= $500,000.  Score = 7
Lobbying &lt;= $750,000.  Score = 6
Lobbying &lt;= $1,000,000.  Score = 5
Lobbying &lt;= $2,500,000.  Score = 4
Lobbying &lt;= $5,000,000.  Score = 3
Lobbying &lt;= $7,500,000.  Score = 2
Lobbying &lt;= $10,000,000.  Score = 1
Lobbying &gt; $10,000,000.  Score = 0

PERFORMANCE OF INDUSTRY PEERS
The Clorox Company: $0.  Score: 10
Colgate-Palmolive: &lt;$10,000.  Score: 9
Kimberly-Clark: $100,000.  Score: 9
Unilever United States, Inc.: $540,000.  Score: 6
Procter &amp; Gamble: $2,794,278.  Score: 3

There are three flaws in my analysis:

The first flaw: The Center for Public Integrity’s most recent data is from 2004.  I would have preferred to use 2006 data.  As far as I can gather, this delay is due to the process of reporting by the company, collection by the Senate oversight body, and publication by The Center for Public Integrity.

The second flaw: My analysis is limited to corporate lobbying expenditures on the federal government of the USA.  So corporate spending on political campaigns and local or state governments are not included.  I am not aware of any data on local and state governments, though some data may be available for political campaigns through organizations such as the now-defunct BuyBlue.org.  

My analysis does not address corporate lobbying expenditures in other countries.  The USA requires corporations to disclose lobbying expenditures, so data is available from NGOs like The Center for Public Integrity.  [The U.S. Congress should be commended for its leadership on this issue.]  The European Union, regrettably, does not require such disclosure.  I have not searched for data in other countries.  The result is that my analysis is probably unfair to American corporations, which would naturally spend more money lobbying the U.S. government than their European counterparts.  For example, the American household products company Procter &amp; Gamble spends much more on U.S. federal lobbying than its Anglo-Dutch rival Unilever (through Unilever United States, Inc.), but it may well be that Unilever spends more than Procter &amp; Gamble in lobbying the European Union.  

I experimented with setting lower criteria for foreign companies, but that criteria seemed even more arbitrary than the existing criteria: Should foreign companies spend one half of what their American industry peers spend on U.S. federal lobbying?  One third?  One tenth?  Things get even more complicated when we consider whether “Unilever United States, Inc.” and “BP America” should be considered American or foreign.  I finally gave up and decided to use a single set of criteria.  I believe the solution is to add more reviews to this database about corporate lobbying of non-USA governments.  I encourage anyone who is up for the challenge!   

The third flaw: Companies are judged according to absolute dollars spent on lobbying, without any regard to industry norms or company size.  Ignoring industry norms is not really a problem for our purposes, because consumers are usually interested in the marginal difference in performance of industry peers.  The question for the consumer is Exxon vs. Shell, not Exxon vs. Kraft.  [Setting aside the important question of gas vs. hybrid electric.]  So we should not be concerned if certain industries (e.g., oil, pharma, banking) tend to get lower lobbying scores for high lobbying expenditures; consumers will simply be interested in who is comparatively better or worse within those industries.  

Ignoring company size, on the other hand, is problematic.  One might plausibly argue that large companies are entitled to spend more on lobbying in order to defend broader interests with larger impacts on public life.  I experimented with criteria that accounts for company size by measuring the proportion of lobbying expenditures to annual revenues.  The exercise was enlightening.  ExxonMobil, for example, spent $7.7 million on U.S. federal lobbying in 2004, which was no surprise to me.  But I was surprised to learn that ExxonMobil’s lobbying expenditures that year amounted to only a tiny fraction of 1% of its annual revenues of $270 billion.  Put another way, ExxonMobil spent $28.40 on federal lobbying for each $1 million in revenue in the year 2004.  I was stunned at how small this fraction is for ExxonMobil and other major corporations I reviewed.  I was even more surprised at the ratio for a much smaller agribusiness corporation, Cargill, with $460,000 in lobbying expenditures and $230 million in annual revenues in 2004.  For Cargill, the math works out to $2,000 on federal lobbying per $1 million in revenue, more than 70 times the proportion that ExxonMobil spends!  

So the question is, how do we define “high performance” in terms of lobbying expenditures?  Should we reward companies that spend less?  Or reward companies that spend less, relative to their budget?  The advantage of measuring proportions is that it creates a smoother, incremental incentive for any company – large or small – to reduce their lobbying expenditures.  The disadvantage, however, is that the proportions will swing wildly with changes in the company’s reported revenues, reducing the incentive to pay attention to lobbying expenditures.  Moreover, the real-world effect of lobbying dollars is absolute; ExxonMobil’s $7.7 million will have a much greater effect than Cargill’s $460,000 on our governance and politics.  I therefore rejected the proportional criteria in favor of measuring simple, absolute lobbying expenditures, with the recognition that large corporations will tend to get lower scores.

I encourage anyone interested in this issue to improve upon this methodology so that we can develop a robust analysis and fair scoring for corporate lobbying expenditures.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>The Center for Public Integrity
http://www.publicintegrity.org/lobby/profile.aspx?act=industries&amp;year=2003&amp;in=74&amp;sub=1

Fortune Global 500.
http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/global500/2005/index.html
</r_sources>
        <co_id>8</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>19</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-25 11:24:26</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>74</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>10</r_score>
        <r_comment>This review is part of a series of reviews that I am submitting about various companies’ lobbying expenditures, using data from The Center for Public Integrity’s “Lobby Watch” program.  I begin with an assessment of an individual company’s performance.  I then specify the criteria I used for this series, and I show comparative scores for industry peers.  I conclude each review with a detailed discussion of the challenges and weaknesses to my approach.

The Clorox Company has an excellent record with respect to how much it spends on lobbying the U.S. federal government.  According to The Center for Public Integrity, The Clorox Company did not spend any money on federal lobbying in 2004, outshining its industry peers.  (2004 is the latest year for which data is available.)  

After some contemplation, I decided to use simple criteria for converting a company’s lobbying expenditures to a 0-10 score: the less a company spends, the higher its score.  According to my criteria, The Clorox Company deserves a score of 10.  

CRITERIA
Lobbying = $0.  Score = 10
Lobbying &lt;= $100,000.  Score = 9
Lobbying &lt;= $250,000.  Score = 8
Lobbying &lt;= $500,000.  Score = 7
Lobbying &lt;= $750,000.  Score = 6
Lobbying &lt;= $1,000,000.  Score = 5
Lobbying &lt;= $2,500,000.  Score = 4
Lobbying &lt;= $5,000,000.  Score = 3
Lobbying &lt;= $7,500,000.  Score = 2
Lobbying &lt;= $10,000,000.  Score = 1
Lobbying &gt; $10,000,000.  Score = 0

PERFORMANCE OF INDUSTRY PEERS
The Clorox Company: $0.  Score: 10
Colgate-Palmolive: &lt;$10,000.  Score: 9
Kimberly-Clark: $100,000.  Score: 9
Unilever United States, Inc.: $540,000.  Score: 6
Procter &amp; Gamble: $2,794,278.  Score: 3

There are three flaws in my analysis:

The first flaw: The Center for Public Integrity’s most recent data is from 2004.  I would have preferred to use 2006 data.  As far as I can gather, this delay is due to the process of reporting by the company, collection by the Senate oversight body, and publication by The Center for Public Integrity.

The second flaw: My analysis is limited to corporate lobbying expenditures on the federal government of the USA.  So corporate spending on political campaigns and local or state governments are not included.  I am not aware of any data on local and state governments, though some data may be available for political campaigns through organizations such as the now-defunct BuyBlue.org.  

My analysis does not address corporate lobbying expenditures in other countries.  The USA requires corporations to disclose lobbying expenditures, so data is available from NGOs like The Center for Public Integrity.  [The U.S. Congress should be commended for its leadership on this issue.]  The European Union, regrettably, does not require such disclosure.  I have not searched for data in other countries.  The result is that my analysis is probably unfair to American corporations, which would naturally spend more money lobbying the U.S. government than their European counterparts.  For example, the American household products company Procter &amp; Gamble spends much more on U.S. federal lobbying than its Anglo-Dutch rival Unilever (through Unilever United States, Inc.), but it may well be that Unilever spends more than Procter &amp; Gamble in lobbying the European Union.  

I experimented with setting lower criteria for foreign companies, but that criteria seemed even more arbitrary than the existing criteria: Should foreign companies spend one half of what their American industry peers spend on U.S. federal lobbying?  One third?  One tenth?  Things get even more complicated when we consider whether “Unilever United States, Inc.” and “BP America” should be considered American or foreign.  I finally gave up and decided to use a single set of criteria.  I believe the solution is to add more reviews to this database about corporate lobbying of non-USA governments.  I encourage anyone who is up for the challenge!   

The third flaw: Companies are judged according to absolute dollars spent on lobbying, without any regard to industry norms or company size.  Ignoring industry norms is not really a problem for our purposes, because consumers are usually interested in the marginal difference in performance of industry peers.  The question for the consumer is Exxon vs. Shell, not Exxon vs. Kraft.  [Setting aside the important question of gas vs. hybrid electric.]  So we should not be concerned if certain industries (e.g., oil, pharma, banking) tend to get lower lobbying scores for high lobbying expenditures; consumers will simply be interested in who is comparatively better or worse within those industries.  

Ignoring company size, on the other hand, is problematic.  One might plausibly argue that large companies are entitled to spend more on lobbying in order to defend broader interests with larger impacts on public life.  I experimented with criteria that accounts for company size by measuring the proportion of lobbying expenditures to annual revenues.  The exercise was enlightening.  ExxonMobil, for example, spent $7.7 million on U.S. federal lobbying in 2004, which was no surprise to me.  But I was surprised to learn that ExxonMobil’s lobbying expenditures that year amounted to only a tiny fraction of 1% of its annual revenues of $270 billion.  Put another way, ExxonMobil spent $28.40 on federal lobbying for each $1 million in revenue in the year 2004.  I was stunned at how small this fraction is for ExxonMobil and other major corporations I reviewed.  I was even more surprised at the ratio for a much smaller agribusiness corporation, Cargill, with $460,000 in lobbying expenditures and $230 million in annual revenues in 2004.  For Cargill, the math works out to $2,000 on federal lobbying per $1 million in revenue, more than 70 times the proportion that ExxonMobil spends!  

So the question is, how do we define “high performance” in terms of lobbying expenditures?  Should we reward companies that spend less?  Or reward companies that spend less, relative to their budget?  The advantage of measuring proportions is that it creates a smoother, incremental incentive for any company – large or small – to reduce their lobbying expenditures.  The disadvantage, however, is that the proportions will swing wildly with changes in the company’s reported revenues, reducing the incentive to pay attention to lobbying expenditures.  Moreover, the real-world effect of lobbying dollars is absolute; ExxonMobil’s $7.7 million will have a much greater effect than Cargill’s $460,000 on our governance and politics.  I therefore rejected the proportional criteria in favor of measuring simple, absolute lobbying expenditures, with the recognition that large corporations will tend to get lower scores.

I encourage anyone interested in this issue to improve upon this methodology so that we can develop a robust analysis and fair scoring for corporate lobbying expenditures.
</r_comment>
        <r_sources>The Center for Public Integrity
http://www.publicintegrity.org/lobby/profile.aspx?act=industries&amp;year=2003&amp;in=74&amp;sub=1

Fortune Global 500.
http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/global500/2005/index.html
</r_sources>
        <co_id>13</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>19</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-25 11:27:49</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>75</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>6</r_score>
        <r_comment>This review is part of a series of reviews that I am submitting about various companies’ lobbying expenditures, using data from The Center for Public Integrity’s “Lobby Watch” program.  I begin with an assessment of an individual company’s performance.  I then specify the criteria I used for this series, and I show comparative scores for industry peers.  I conclude each review with a detailed discussion of the challenges and weaknesses to my approach.

Unilever has a mediocre record with respect to how much it spends on lobbying the U.S. federal government.  According to The Center for Public Integrity, Unilever United States, Inc. spent $540,000 on federal lobbying in 2004, more than any of its industry peers except Procter &amp; Gamble.  (2004 is the latest year for which data is available.)  

After some contemplation, I decided to use simple criteria for converting a company’s lobbying expenditures to a 0-10 score: the less a company spends, the higher its score.  According to my criteria, Unilever deserves a score of 6.  

CRITERIA
Lobbying = $0.  Score = 10
Lobbying &lt;= $100,000.  Score = 9
Lobbying &lt;= $250,000.  Score = 8
Lobbying &lt;= $500,000.  Score = 7
Lobbying &lt;= $750,000.  Score = 6
Lobbying &lt;= $1,000,000.  Score = 5
Lobbying &lt;= $2,500,000.  Score = 4
Lobbying &lt;= $5,000,000.  Score = 3
Lobbying &lt;= $7,500,000.  Score = 2
Lobbying &lt;= $10,000,000.  Score = 1
Lobbying &gt; $10,000,000.  Score = 0

PERFORMANCE OF INDUSTRY PEERS
The Clorox Company: $0.  Score: 10
Colgate-Palmolive: &lt;$10,000.  Score: 9
Kimberly-Clark: $100,000.  Score: 9
Unilever United States, Inc.: $540,000.  Score: 6
Procter &amp; Gamble: $2,794,278.  Score: 3

There are three flaws in my analysis:

The first flaw: The Center for Public Integrity’s most recent data is from 2004.  I would have preferred to use 2006 data.  As far as I can gather, this delay is due to the process of reporting by the company, collection by the Senate oversight body, and publication by The Center for Public Integrity.

The second flaw: My analysis is limited to corporate lobbying expenditures on the federal government of the USA.  So corporate spending on political campaigns and local or state governments are not included.  I am not aware of any data on local and state governments, though some data may be available for political campaigns through organizations such as the now-defunct BuyBlue.org.  

My analysis does not address corporate lobbying expenditures in other countries.  The USA requires corporations to disclose lobbying expenditures, so data is available from NGOs like The Center for Public Integrity.  [The U.S. Congress should be commended for its leadership on this issue.]  The European Union, regrettably, does not require such disclosure.  I have not searched for data in other countries.  The result is that my analysis is probably unfair to American corporations, which would naturally spend more money lobbying the U.S. government than their European counterparts.  For example, the American household products company Procter &amp; Gamble spends much more on U.S. federal lobbying than its Anglo-Dutch rival Unilever (through Unilever United States, Inc.), but it may well be that Unilever spends more than Procter &amp; Gamble in lobbying the European Union.  

I experimented with setting lower criteria for foreign companies, but that criteria seemed even more arbitrary than the existing criteria: Should foreign companies spend one half of what their American industry peers spend on U.S. federal lobbying?  One third?  One tenth?  Things get even more complicated when we consider whether “Unilever United States, Inc.” and “BP America” should be considered American or foreign.  I finally gave up and decided to use a single set of criteria.  I believe the solution is to add more reviews to this database about corporate lobbying of non-USA governments.  I encourage anyone who is up for the challenge!   

The third flaw: Companies are judged according to absolute dollars spent on lobbying, without any regard to industry norms or company size.  Ignoring industry norms is not really a problem for our purposes, because consumers are usually interested in the marginal difference in performance of industry peers.  The question for the consumer is Exxon vs. Shell, not Exxon vs. Kraft.  [Setting aside the important question of gas vs. hybrid electric.]  So we should not be concerned if certain industries (e.g., oil, pharma, banking) tend to get lower lobbying scores for high lobbying expenditures; consumers will simply be interested in who is comparatively better or worse within those industries.  

Ignoring company size, on the other hand, is problematic.  One might plausibly argue that large companies are entitled to spend more on lobbying in order to defend broader interests with larger impacts on public life.  I experimented with criteria that accounts for company size by measuring the proportion of lobbying expenditures to annual revenues.  The exercise was enlightening.  ExxonMobil, for example, spent $7.7 million on U.S. federal lobbying in 2004, which was no surprise to me.  But I was surprised to learn that ExxonMobil’s lobbying expenditures that year amounted to only a tiny fraction of 1% of its annual revenues of $270 billion.  Put another way, ExxonMobil spent $28.40 on federal lobbying for each $1 million in revenue in the year 2004.  I was stunned at how small this fraction is for ExxonMobil and other major corporations I reviewed.  I was even more surprised at the ratio for a much smaller agribusiness corporation, Cargill, with $460,000 in lobbying expenditures and $230 million in annual revenues in 2004.  For Cargill, the math works out to $2,000 on federal lobbying per $1 million in revenue, more than 70 times the proportion that ExxonMobil spends!  

So the question is, how do we define “high performance” in terms of lobbying expenditures?  Should we reward companies that spend less?  Or reward companies that spend less, relative to their budget?  The advantage of measuring proportions is that it creates a smoother, incremental incentive for any company – large or small – to reduce their lobbying expenditures.  The disadvantage, however, is that the proportions will swing wildly with changes in the company’s reported revenues, reducing the incentive to pay attention to lobbying expenditures.  Moreover, the real-world effect of lobbying dollars is absolute; ExxonMobil’s $7.7 million will have a much greater effect than Cargill’s $460,000 on our governance and politics.  I therefore rejected the proportional criteria in favor of measuring simple, absolute lobbying expenditures, with the recognition that large corporations will tend to get lower scores.

I encourage anyone interested in this issue to improve upon this methodology so that we can develop a robust analysis and fair scoring for corporate lobbying expenditures.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>The Center for Public Integrity
http://www.publicintegrity.org/lobby/profile.aspx?act=industries&amp;year=2003&amp;in=74&amp;sub=1

Fortune Global 500.
http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/global500/2005/index.html
</r_sources>
        <co_id>14</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>19</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-25 11:31:01</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>76</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>9</r_score>
        <r_comment>This review is part of a series of reviews that I am submitting about various companies’ lobbying expenditures, using data from The Center for Public Integrity’s “Lobby Watch” program.  I begin with an assessment of an individual company’s performance.  I then specify the criteria I used for this series, and I show comparative scores for industry peers.  I conclude each review with a detailed discussion of the challenges and weaknesses to my approach.

Kimberly-Clark has a relatively good record with respect to how much it spends on lobbying the U.S. federal government.  According to The Center for Public Integrity, Kimberly-Clark spent $100,000 on federal lobbying in 2004, much less than larger household products companies like Procter &amp; Gamble and Unilever.  (2004 is the latest year for which data is available.)  

After some contemplation, I decided to use simple criteria for converting a company’s lobbying expenditures to a 0-10 score: the less a company spends, the higher its score.  According to my criteria, Kimberly-Clark deserves a score of 9.  

CRITERIA
Lobbying = $0.  Score = 10
Lobbying &lt;= $100,000.  Score = 9
Lobbying &lt;= $250,000.  Score = 8
Lobbying &lt;= $500,000.  Score = 7
Lobbying &lt;= $750,000.  Score = 6
Lobbying &lt;= $1,000,000.  Score = 5
Lobbying &lt;= $2,500,000.  Score = 4
Lobbying &lt;= $5,000,000.  Score = 3
Lobbying &lt;= $7,500,000.  Score = 2
Lobbying &lt;= $10,000,000.  Score = 1
Lobbying &gt; $10,000,000.  Score = 0

PERFORMANCE OF INDUSTRY PEERS
The Clorox Company: $0.  Score: 10
Colgate-Palmolive: &lt;$10,000.  Score: 9
Kimberly-Clark: $100,000.  Score: 9
Unilever United States, Inc.: $540,000.  Score: 6
Procter &amp; Gamble: $2,794,278.  Score: 3

There are three flaws in my analysis:

The first flaw: The Center for Public Integrity’s most recent data is from 2004.  I would have preferred to use 2006 data.  As far as I can gather, this delay is due to the process of reporting by the company, collection by the Senate oversight body, and publication by The Center for Public Integrity.

The second flaw: My analysis is limited to corporate lobbying expenditures on the federal government of the USA.  So corporate spending on political campaigns and local or state governments are not included.  I am not aware of any data on local and state governments, though some data may be available for political campaigns through organizations such as the now-defunct BuyBlue.org.  

My analysis does not address corporate lobbying expenditures in other countries.  The USA requires corporations to disclose lobbying expenditures, so data is available from NGOs like The Center for Public Integrity.  [The U.S. Congress should be commended for its leadership on this issue.]  The European Union, regrettably, does not require such disclosure.  I have not searched for data in other countries.  The result is that my analysis is probably unfair to American corporations, which would naturally spend more money lobbying the U.S. government than their European counterparts.  For example, the American household products company Procter &amp; Gamble spends much more on U.S. federal lobbying than its Anglo-Dutch rival Unilever (through Unilever United States, Inc.), but it may well be that Unilever spends more than Procter &amp; Gamble in lobbying the European Union.  

I experimented with setting lower criteria for foreign companies, but that criteria seemed even more arbitrary than the existing criteria: Should foreign companies spend one half of what their American industry peers spend on U.S. federal lobbying?  One third?  One tenth?  Things get even more complicated when we consider whether “Unilever United States, Inc.” and “BP America” should be considered American or foreign.  I finally gave up and decided to use a single set of criteria.  I believe the solution is to add more reviews to this database about corporate lobbying of non-USA governments.  I encourage anyone who is up for the challenge!   

The third flaw: Companies are judged according to absolute dollars spent on lobbying, without any regard to industry norms or company size.  Ignoring industry norms is not really a problem for our purposes, because consumers are usually interested in the marginal difference in performance of industry peers.  The question for the consumer is Exxon vs. Shell, not Exxon vs. Kraft.  [Setting aside the important question of gas vs. hybrid electric.]  So we should not be concerned if certain industries (e.g., oil, pharma, banking) tend to get lower lobbying scores for high lobbying expenditures; consumers will simply be interested in who is comparatively better or worse within those industries.  

Ignoring company size, on the other hand, is problematic.  One might plausibly argue that large companies are entitled to spend more on lobbying in order to defend broader interests with larger impacts on public life.  I experimented with criteria that accounts for company size by measuring the proportion of lobbying expenditures to annual revenues.  The exercise was enlightening.  ExxonMobil, for example, spent $7.7 million on U.S. federal lobbying in 2004, which was no surprise to me.  But I was surprised to learn that ExxonMobil’s lobbying expenditures that year amounted to only a tiny fraction of 1% of its annual revenues of $270 billion.  Put another way, ExxonMobil spent $28.40 on federal lobbying for each $1 million in revenue in the year 2004.  I was stunned at how small this fraction is for ExxonMobil and other major corporations I reviewed.  I was even more surprised at the ratio for a much smaller agribusiness corporation, Cargill, with $460,000 in lobbying expenditures and $230 million in annual revenues in 2004.  For Cargill, the math works out to $2,000 on federal lobbying per $1 million in revenue, more than 70 times the proportion that ExxonMobil spends!  

So the question is, how do we define “high performance” in terms of lobbying expenditures?  Should we reward companies that spend less?  Or reward companies that spend less, relative to their budget?  The advantage of measuring proportions is that it creates a smoother, incremental incentive for any company – large or small – to reduce their lobbying expenditures.  The disadvantage, however, is that the proportions will swing wildly with changes in the company’s reported revenues, reducing the incentive to pay attention to lobbying expenditures.  Moreover, the real-world effect of lobbying dollars is absolute; ExxonMobil’s $7.7 million will have a much greater effect than Cargill’s $460,000 on our governance and politics.  I therefore rejected the proportional criteria in favor of measuring simple, absolute lobbying expenditures, with the recognition that large corporations will tend to get lower scores.

I encourage anyone interested in this issue to improve upon this methodology so that we can develop a robust analysis and fair scoring for corporate lobbying expenditures.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>The Center for Public Integrity
http://www.publicintegrity.org/lobby/profile.aspx?act=industries&amp;year=2003&amp;in=74&amp;sub=1

Fortune Global 500.
http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/global500/2005/index.html</r_sources>
        <co_id>10</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>19</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-25 11:34:15</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>77</r_id>
        <uname>kmagida</uname>
        <r_score>1</r_score>
        <r_comment>Chevron is invested in Myanmar and is refusing to back out of their project there even though investment there has been made illegal and the  junta there has cracked down on pro-democracy demonstrators.  They claim to only be a minority shareholder with no influence but they have not sufficiently documented the benefits of them remaining in the country.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/10/29/bloomberg/bxenergy.php International Herald Tribune, Oct. 30, 2007 &quot;Chevron digs in its heels over Myanmar&quot;</r_sources>
        <co_id>2</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>24</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-30 06:49:01</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>78</r_id>
        <uname>kmagida</uname>
        <r_score>1</r_score>
        <r_comment>Total is heavily invested in Burma/Myanmar and is refusing to divest following the crackdowns on pro-democracy demonstrators in that country. While divestment is a thorny issue and sometimes isn't always the correct one, there are limited economic opportunities for pressuring the junta.  Total claims their work is beneficial to Thailand and the Burmese people but there are indications that most of the money is going to the military junta.  They claim someone else would take their spot but this is a common protest towards divestment and one that is easy to use and ignores the aims of divestment.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>http://www.socialfunds.com/news/article.cgi/2402.html</r_sources>
        <co_id>7</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>24</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-30 07:00:47</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>79</r_id>
        <uname>kmagida</uname>
        <r_score>8</r_score>
        <r_comment>They have been rated highly in the publication Canada's top 100 Employers which is a major Canadian publication about Labor Practices.  They are lauded for their employee benefits, monetary and otherwise which includes health care, benefits below, and at market salaries.  They also give provide substantial day-care at the office and fully paid maternity leave for 17 weeks for all parents.  They also maintain a pension fund. This rating is based on their relative success in this category but due to some non-exceptional ratings in salary and vacation they don't receive a 9 or 10. 

Health benefits:
Health Benefits at a Glance:L'Oréal's health plan includes the following coverage: routine dental (90% of eligible costs, to $2000 each year); restorative dental; orthodontics (50% of eligible costs with a lifetime maximum of $1000); eyecare (to $175 every 2 years); prescription drug; massage therapy; physiotherapy; chiropractor; osteopathy; podiatry; acupuncture; naturopathy; ergotherapy; speech therapy; personal and family counselling; employee assistance plan (EAP) for substance abuse/mental health; semi-private hospital room; medical equipment and supplies; home care; travel medical insurance. </r_comment>
        <r_sources>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Top_100_Employers
http://www.eluta.ca/einfo?en=L'Or%E9al+Canada+Inc.&amp;ri=01c7e29b00765143356d9ab408206c1d&amp;rk=cf53704cc356bed006aaab6ec72e916d</r_sources>
        <co_id>11</co_id>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
        <top_id>29</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-30 07:22:29</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>80</r_id>
        <uname>kmagida</uname>
        <r_score>9</r_score>
        <r_comment>L'Oreal seems to make it a policy to hire equally from men and women and there is no apparent drop-off once management is considered.  Also Canada's Top 100 Employers publication claims that 51 percent of all employees are minority.  The sponsor initiatives for women in science and their controlling shareholder is a women albeit the founder's daughter. Most of this data is collected in North America while they are based in Europe.

Workforce at a Glance:Number of full-time employees: 1200. At this location: 286. Worldwide: 52403. Percentage of Canadian workforce employed on contract basis: 2%. Percentage of employees who are women: 64. Of managers: 55. Percentage of employees who are visible minorities: 51. Resumes received by their HR staff in past year: 12000. Weeks of vacation their HR manager took last year: 5. Average employee age: 37. Years longest-serving employee has worked there: 39. </r_comment>
        <r_sources>http://www.eluta.ca/einfo?en=L'Or%E9al+Canada+Inc.&amp;ri=01c7e29b00765143356d9ab408206c1d&amp;rk=cf53704cc356bed006aaab6ec72e916d
http://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2007-05/epr-fry051807.php
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LOreal</r_sources>
        <co_id>11</co_id>
        <cat_id>3</cat_id>
        <top_id>33</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-10-30 07:30:16</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>81</r_id>
        <uname>iwohl</uname>
        <r_score>2</r_score>
        <r_comment>Last week, the Supreme Court granted certiorari to the Exxon Valdez case, in which fishermen and indigenous people sued the oil company, claiming their livelihoods had been destroyed by the Alaskan oil spill.  Certiorari means the case will continue grinding along for years.  In 1994, a jury ruled in favor of the plaintiffs and awarded them $5 billion in damages, but Exxon's lawyers have successfully flooded the system with motions and appeals, preventing a resolution for 13 years.  (Some plaintiffs have died in the interim.)  I give ExxonMobil a &quot;2&quot; rather than a &quot;0&quot; because I'm sympathetic to the argument that this is at least partly the fault of the 9th US Circuit Court of Appeals, which is supposed to prevent this kind of stalling and legal manipulation.  But it's disheartening to see ExxonMobil fighting tooth and nail to avoid reckoning for their tragedy.</r_comment>
        <r_sources></r_sources>
        <co_id>4</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>19</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-11-12 18:04:47</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>82</r_id>
        <uname>iwohl</uname>
        <r_score>3</r_score>
        <r_comment>This YouTube video is pretty good:  http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3u6Qh099AK0
It points out the cynical paradigm of Unilever and other corporations that use positive social messages only when it's profitable.

The gist of it is that Unilever owns both Dove and Axe.  The recent Dove advertising campaign seems to be at least making steps towards a less harmful ideal of the feminine physique (e.g. the &quot;Dove Evolution&quot; commercial, also on YouTube).  But this is undermined by Axe advertisements, which are impressively demeaning towards women.  (Even if you find them entertaining, it's probably not the worldview you'd want to bequeath to your daughter.)  And Unilever sells more products inasmuch as consumers believe the people behind Dove actually care about addressing body image issues in our society.

I give them a &quot;3&quot; because there are worse things than being a hypocrite.  Maybe we shouldn't expect corporations not to play both sides when there's money to be made.  But there is real damage done here:  it gives cause for cynicism and suspicion whenever anyone looks like they're doing a good thing.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3u6Qh099AK0</r_sources>
        <co_id>14</co_id>
        <cat_id>7</cat_id>
        <top_id>35</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-11-12 19:05:10</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>83</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>7</r_score>
        <r_comment>Shell's US subsidiary - Shell Oil Products US - announced in November 2007 that it would collaborate with biotech company Codexis, Inc. to explore new ways to convert biomass to biofuels.

I personally have my doubts about biofuels, but I'm glad to see that Shell is exploring the options.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>http://www.forbes.com/home/feeds/afx/2006/11/16/afx3181584.html
</r_sources>
        <co_id>5</co_id>
        <cat_id>2</cat_id>
        <top_id>12</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-11-26 10:52:38</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>86</r_id>
        <uname>kmagida</uname>
        <r_score>8</r_score>
        <r_comment>Henkel has received high marks for their Sustainability report from the Econ Verlag publishing house and the Handelsblatt business newspaper in their home country of Germany. They also indicate in their Sustainability Report on page 32 that they attempt to follow the GRI (Global Reporting Initiative) criteria.  The score of 8 is derived from my uncertainty of the legitimacy of the ranking and Henkel choosing to use it to imply they are Sustainable.  The report itself is clear and comprehensive.</r_comment>
        <r_sources>http://www.henkel.com/com/content_data/Sustainability_Report_06_e.pdf a PDF of the Sustainability report
 
News Article announcing ranking
http://www.agencyfaqs.com/perl/news/company_briefs/index.html?id=23148</r_sources>
        <co_id>9</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>25</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2007-11-29 18:08:39</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>97</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>0</r_score>
        <r_comment>On November 19, 2007, Human Rights Watch (HRW) released a report criticizing oil and gas companies for operating in Myanmar (Burma) and consequently providing a “crucial source of support” to the military junta that controls the government.  I have read arguments by various oil and gas companies that defend their continued operations in Myanmar, but in my opinion HRW’s critique is more persuasive.  HRW makes a strong case that these business operations directly benefit the junta to the detriment of the people of Myanmar. (I discuss both arguments below.) 
 
Sinopec is one of the companies that continues to operate in Myanmar.  I therefore give Sinopec a score of 0 for its performance in Investment &amp; Procurement Practices, recognizing that Sinopec may exhibit different performance in other countries or in other aspects of investments and procurements.  (Since I am focusing on one country of operations here, I simply award a zero to companies that operate in Myanmar and a 10 to companies that do not.)

The following excerpts from HRW’s report are worth quoting at length, because they explain how these oil and gas business deals work:

“Foreign companies sign contracts with the state-run Myanmar Oil and Gas Enterprise (MOGE). Under these contracts, the companies get permission to drill for oil and gas in a designated geographic area known as a block… The “production-sharing contracts” between MOGE and the companies specify the fees and taxes the companies have to pay to the government of Burma. They also give the government the right to become a partner in the project after a period of time, if it looks promising. In other words, foreign companies spend money up front to explore for and produce petroleum, but Burma’s military gets a cut of the sale of oil and gas produced from these fields once initial costs are recovered… Burma’s military government relies heavily on the oil and gas sector to sustain itself in power. It earned approximately $2.16 billion in 2006 from sales of natural gas, which accounted for half of Burma’s exports and represents its single largest source of foreign exchange.” 
 
Of the oil and gas companies that do operate in Myanmar, Total provides the most eloquent defense.  Other companies, such as Daewoo, dismiss criticism with such crude remarks as “Politics is politics.  Economics is economics” (as reported by HRW).  Here is what Total has to say about its operations in Myanmar:

“We are convinced that through our presence we are helping to improve the daily lives of tens of thousands of people who benefit from our social and economic initiatives. By promoting responsible behavior, our local teams can serve as a model for business and political leaders looking for ways to address the country's human rights issues.

We would like to thank all those who have encouraged us to pursue our actions to help the local people and enhance their well-being through the defense of common values. To those who ask us to leave the country, we reply that far from solving Myanmar's problems, a forced withdrawal would only lead to our replacement by other operators probably less committed to the ethical principles guiding all our initiatives. Our departure could cause the population even greater hardship and is thus an unacceptable risk.”

This pragmatic argument might be compelling if we believed that an “ethical” company like Total has a net positive impact on the people of Myanmar.  But HRW points out that the very presence of these oil and gas companies (including Total) sustains the oppressive junta that has ruined the entire country.  It’s hard to imagine how any localized benefits from business operations can outweigh the overwhelming social costs of financially supporting the junta.

You can read more about Total’s position by following the links I provide below in “Sources.”  Total’s comments are interesting, but – in my opinion – ultimately unpersuasive when compared to HRW’s critique.  And since Total has tried harder than any other company to justify its continued presence in Myanmar, I doubt that you will find good reasons to support any company in operating there.  
</r_comment>
        <r_sources>NY Times on the monk protests and junta crackdown in September 2007: http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/30/weekinreview/30mydans.html

Human Rights Watch criticizes oil and gas companies for propping up the junta:
http://www.hrw.org/campaigns/burma/drilling/Burma_table3_companies.pdf

Total defends its presence in Myanmar (Burma):
http://burma.total.com/
http://burma.total.com/en/news/p_5_4.htm
http://burma.total.com/en/publications/burma_campaign.pdf
</r_sources>
        <co_id>6</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>22</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2008-01-03 12:32:39</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>98</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>0</r_score>
        <r_comment>On November 19, 2007, Human Rights Watch (HRW) released a report criticizing oil and gas companies for operating in Myanmar (Burma) and consequently providing a “crucial source of support” to the military junta that controls the government.  I have read arguments by various oil and gas companies that defend their continued operations in Myanmar, but in my opinion HRW’s critique is more persuasive.  HRW makes a strong case that these business operations directly benefit the junta to the detriment of the people of Myanmar. (I discuss both arguments below.) 
 
Total is one of the companies that continues to operate in Myanmar.  I therefore give Total a score of 0 for its performance in Investment &amp; Procurement Practices, recognizing that Total may exhibit different performance in other countries or in other aspects of investments and procurements.  (Since I am focusing on one country of operations here, I simply award a zero to companies that operate in Myanmar and a 10 to companies that do not.)

The following excerpts from HRW’s report are worth quoting at length, because they explain how these oil and gas business deals work:

“Foreign companies sign contracts with the state-run Myanmar Oil and Gas Enterprise (MOGE). Under these contracts, the companies get permission to drill for oil and gas in a designated geographic area known as a block… The “production-sharing contracts” between MOGE and the companies specify the fees and taxes the companies have to pay to the government of Burma. They also give the government the right to become a partner in the project after a period of time, if it looks promising. In other words, foreign companies spend money up front to explore for and produce petroleum, but Burma’s military gets a cut of the sale of oil and gas produced from these fields once initial costs are recovered… Burma’s military government relies heavily on the oil and gas sector to sustain itself in power. It earned approximately $2.16 billion in 2006 from sales of natural gas, which accounted for half of Burma’s exports and represents its single largest source of foreign exchange.”  

Of the oil and gas companies that do operate in Myanmar, Total provides the most eloquent defense.  Other companies, such as Daewoo, dismiss criticism with such crude remarks as “Politics is politics.  Economics is economics” (as reported by HRW).  Here is what Total has to say about its operations in Myanmar:

“We are convinced that through our presence we are helping to improve the daily lives of tens of thousands of people who benefit from our social and economic initiatives. By promoting responsible behavior, our local teams can serve as a model for business and political leaders looking for ways to address the country's human rights issues.

We would like to thank all those who have encouraged us to pursue our actions to help the local people and enhance their well-being through the defense of common values. To those who ask us to leave the country, we reply that far from solving Myanmar's problems, a forced withdrawal would only lead to our replacement by other operators probably less committed to the ethical principles guiding all our initiatives. Our departure could cause the population even greater hardship and is thus an unacceptable risk.”

This pragmatic argument might be compelling if we believed that an “ethical” company like Total has a net positive impact on the people of Myanmar.  But HRW points out that the very presence of these oil and gas companies (including Total) sustains the oppressive junta that has ruined the entire country.  It’s hard to imagine how any localized benefits from business operations can outweigh the overwhelming social costs of financially supporting the junta.

You can read more about Total’s position by following the links I provide below in “Sources.”  Total’s comments are interesting, but – in my opinion – ultimately unpersuasive when compared to HRW’s critique.  And since Total has tried harder than any other company to justify its continued presence in Myanmar, I doubt that you will find good reasons to support any company in operating there.  
</r_comment>
        <r_sources>NY Times on the monk protests and junta crackdown in September 2007: http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/30/weekinreview/30mydans.html

Human Rights Watch criticizes oil and gas companies for propping up the junta:
http://www.hrw.org/campaigns/burma/drilling/Burma_table3_companies.pdf

Total defends its presence in Myanmar (Burma):
http://burma.total.com/
http://burma.total.com/en/news/p_5_4.htm
http://burma.total.com/en/publications/burma_campaign.pdf
</r_sources>
        <co_id>7</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>22</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2008-01-03 20:08:32</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>101</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>10</r_score>
        <r_comment>On November 19, 2007, Human Rights Watch (HRW) released a report criticizing oil and gas companies for operating in Myanmar (Burma) and consequently providing a “crucial source of support” to the military junta that controls the government.  I have read arguments by various oil and gas companies that defend their continued operations in Myanmar, but in my opinion HRW’s critique is more persuasive.  HRW makes a strong case that these business operations directly benefit the junta to the detriment of the people of Myanmar. (I discuss both arguments below.)  

Shell does not operate in Myanmar.  I therefore give Shell a score of 10 for its performance in Investment &amp; Procurement Practices, recognizing that Shell may exhibit different performance in other countries or in other aspects of investments and procurements.  

Since I am focusing on one country of operations here, I simply award a zero to companies that operate in Myanmar, such as Total, Chevron and Sinopec.  I award a 10 to companies that do not operate in Myanmar, such as BP, ConocoPhillips, ExxonMobil and Royal Dutch Shell.

The following excerpts from HRW’s report are worth quoting at length, because they explain how these oil and gas business deals work:

“Foreign companies sign contracts with the state-run Myanmar Oil and Gas Enterprise (MOGE). Under these contracts, the companies get permission to drill for oil and gas in a designated geographic area known as a block… The “production-sharing contracts” between MOGE and the companies specify the fees and taxes the companies have to pay to the government of Burma. They also give the government the right to become a partner in the project after a period of time, if it looks promising. In other words, foreign companies spend money up front to explore for and produce petroleum, but Burma’s military gets a cut of the sale of oil and gas produced from these fields once initial costs are recovered… Burma’s military government relies heavily on the oil and gas sector to sustain itself in power. It earned approximately $2.16 billion in 2006 from sales of natural gas, which accounted for half of Burma’s exports and represents its single largest source of foreign exchange.” 
 
Of the oil and gas companies that do operate in Myanmar, Total provides the most eloquent defense.  Other companies, such as Daewoo, dismiss criticism with such crude remarks as “Politics is politics.  Economics is economics” (as reported by HRW).  Here is what Total has to say about its operations in Myanmar:

“We are convinced that through our presence we are helping to improve the daily lives of tens of thousands of people who benefit from our social and economic initiatives. By promoting responsible behavior, our local teams can serve as a model for business and political leaders looking for ways to address the country's human rights issues.

We would like to thank all those who have encouraged us to pursue our actions to help the local people and enhance their well-being through the defense of common values. To those who ask us to leave the country, we reply that far from solving Myanmar's problems, a forced withdrawal would only lead to our replacement by other operators probably less committed to the ethical principles guiding all our initiatives. Our departure could cause the population even greater hardship and is thus an unacceptable risk.”

This pragmatic argument might be compelling if we believed that an “ethical” company like Total has a net positive impact on the people of Myanmar.  But HRW points out that the very presence of these oil and gas companies (including Total) sustains the oppressive junta that has ruined the entire country.  It’s hard to imagine how any localized benefits from business operations can outweigh the overwhelming social costs of financially supporting the junta.

You can read more about Total’s position by following the links I provide below in “Sources.”  Total’s comments are interesting, but – in my opinion – ultimately unpersuasive when compared to HRW’s critique.  And since Total has tried harder than any other company to justify its continued presence in Myanmar, I doubt that you will find good reasons to support any company in operating there. 
</r_comment>
        <r_sources>NY Times on the monk protests and junta crackdown in September 2007: http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/30/weekinreview/30mydans.html

Human Rights Watch criticizes oil and gas companies for propping up the junta:
http://www.hrw.org/campaigns/burma/drilling/Burma_table3_companies.pdf

Total defends its presence in Myanmar (Burma):
http://burma.total.com/
http://burma.total.com/en/news/p_5_4.htm
http://burma.total.com/en/publications/burma_campaign.pdf
</r_sources>
        <co_id>5</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>22</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2008-01-03 20:32:20</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>100</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>0</r_score>
        <r_comment>On November 19, 2007, Human Rights Watch (HRW) released a report criticizing oil and gas companies for operating in Myanmar (Burma) and consequently providing a “crucial source of support” to the military junta that controls the government.  I have read arguments by various oil and gas companies that defend their continued operations in Myanmar, but in my opinion HRW’s critique is more persuasive.  HRW makes a strong case that these business operations directly benefit the junta to the detriment of the people of Myanmar. (I discuss both arguments below.)  

Chevron is one of the companies that continues to operate in Myanmar, through its subsidiary Unocal Myanmar Offshore Company.  I therefore give Chevron a score of 0 for its performance in Investment &amp; Procurement Practices, recognizing that Chevron may exhibit different performance in other countries or in other aspects of investments and procurements.  (Since I am focusing on one country of operations here, I simply award a zero to companies that operate in Myanmar and a 10 to companies that do not.)

The following excerpts from HRW’s report are worth quoting at length, because they explain how these oil and gas business deals work:

“Foreign companies sign contracts with the state-run Myanmar Oil and Gas Enterprise (MOGE). Under these contracts, the companies get permission to drill for oil and gas in a designated geographic area known as a block… The “production-sharing contracts” between MOGE and the companies specify the fees and taxes the companies have to pay to the government of Burma. They also give the government the right to become a partner in the project after a period of time, if it looks promising. In other words, foreign companies spend money up front to explore for and produce petroleum, but Burma’s military gets a cut of the sale of oil and gas produced from these fields once initial costs are recovered… Burma’s military government relies heavily on the oil and gas sector to sustain itself in power. It earned approximately $2.16 billion in 2006 from sales of natural gas, which accounted for half of Burma’s exports and represents its single largest source of foreign exchange.” 
 
Of the oil and gas companies that do operate in Myanmar, Total provides the most eloquent defense.  Other companies, such as Daewoo, dismiss criticism with such crude remarks as “Politics is politics.  Economics is economics” (as reported by HRW).  Here is what Total has to say about its operations in Myanmar:

“We are convinced that through our presence we are helping to improve the daily lives of tens of thousands of people who benefit from our social and economic initiatives. By promoting responsible behavior, our local teams can serve as a model for business and political leaders looking for ways to address the country's human rights issues.

We would like to thank all those who have encouraged us to pursue our actions to help the local people and enhance their well-being through the defense of common values. To those who ask us to leave the country, we reply that far from solving Myanmar's problems, a forced withdrawal would only lead to our replacement by other operators probably less committed to the ethical principles guiding all our initiatives. Our departure could cause the population even greater hardship and is thus an unacceptable risk.”

This pragmatic argument might be compelling if we believed that an “ethical” company like Total has a net positive impact on the people of Myanmar.  But HRW points out that the very presence of these oil and gas companies (including Total) sustains the oppressive junta that has ruined the entire country.  It’s hard to imagine how any localized benefits from business operations can outweigh the overwhelming social costs of financially supporting the junta.

You can read more about Total’s position by following the links I provide below in “Sources.”  Total’s comments are interesting, but – in my opinion – ultimately unpersuasive when compared to HRW’s critique.  And since Total has tried harder than any other company to justify its continued presence in Myanmar, I doubt that you will find good reasons to support any company in operating there. 
</r_comment>
        <r_sources>NY Times on the monk protests and junta crackdown in September 2007: http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/30/weekinreview/30mydans.html

Human Rights Watch criticizes oil and gas companies for propping up the junta:
http://www.hrw.org/campaigns/burma/drilling/Burma_table3_companies.pdf

Total defends its presence in Myanmar (Burma):
http://burma.total.com/
http://burma.total.com/en/news/p_5_4.htm
http://burma.total.com/en/publications/burma_campaign.pdf
</r_sources>
        <co_id>2</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>22</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2008-01-03 20:17:35</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>102</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>10</r_score>
        <r_comment>On November 19, 2007, Human Rights Watch (HRW) released a report criticizing oil and gas companies for operating in Myanmar (Burma) and consequently providing a “crucial source of support” to the military junta that controls the government.  I have read arguments by various oil and gas companies that defend their continued operations in Myanmar, but in my opinion HRW’s critique is more persuasive.  HRW makes a strong case that these business operations directly benefit the junta to the detriment of the people of Myanmar. (I discuss both arguments below.)  

ConocoPhillips does not operate in Myanmar.  I therefore give ConocoPhillips a score of 10 for its performance in Investment &amp; Procurement Practices, recognizing that ConocoPhillips may exhibit different performance in other countries or in other aspects of investments and procurements.  

Since I am focusing on one country of operations here, I simply award a zero to companies that operate in Myanmar, such as Total, Chevron and Sinopec.  I award a 10 to companies that do not operate in Myanmar, such as BP, ConocoPhillips, ExxonMobil and Royal Dutch Shell.

The following excerpts from HRW’s report are worth quoting at length, because they explain how these oil and gas business deals work:

“Foreign companies sign contracts with the state-run Myanmar Oil and Gas Enterprise (MOGE). Under these contracts, the companies get permission to drill for oil and gas in a designated geographic area known as a block… The “production-sharing contracts” between MOGE and the companies specify the fees and taxes the companies have to pay to the government of Burma. They also give the government the right to become a partner in the project after a period of time, if it looks promising. In other words, foreign companies spend money up front to explore for and produce petroleum, but Burma’s military gets a cut of the sale of oil and gas produced from these fields once initial costs are recovered… Burma’s military government relies heavily on the oil and gas sector to sustain itself in power. It earned approximately $2.16 billion in 2006 from sales of natural gas, which accounted for half of Burma’s exports and represents its single largest source of foreign exchange.” 
 
Of the oil and gas companies that do operate in Myanmar, Total provides the most eloquent defense.  Other companies, such as Daewoo, dismiss criticism with such crude remarks as “Politics is politics.  Economics is economics” (as reported by HRW).  Here is what Total has to say about its operations in Myanmar:

“We are convinced that through our presence we are helping to improve the daily lives of tens of thousands of people who benefit from our social and economic initiatives. By promoting responsible behavior, our local teams can serve as a model for business and political leaders looking for ways to address the country's human rights issues.

We would like to thank all those who have encouraged us to pursue our actions to help the local people and enhance their well-being through the defense of common values. To those who ask us to leave the country, we reply that far from solving Myanmar's problems, a forced withdrawal would only lead to our replacement by other operators probably less committed to the ethical principles guiding all our initiatives. Our departure could cause the population even greater hardship and is thus an unacceptable risk.”

This pragmatic argument might be compelling if we believed that an “ethical” company like Total has a net positive impact on the people of Myanmar.  But HRW points out that the very presence of these oil and gas companies (including Total) sustains the oppressive junta that has ruined the entire country.  It’s hard to imagine how any localized benefits from business operations can outweigh the overwhelming social costs of financially supporting the junta.

You can read more about Total’s position by following the links I provide below in “Sources.”  Total’s comments are interesting, but – in my opinion – ultimately unpersuasive when compared to HRW’s critique.  And since Total has tried harder than any other company to justify its continued presence in Myanmar, I doubt that you will find good reasons to support any company in operating there. 
</r_comment>
        <r_sources>NY Times on the monk protests and junta crackdown in September 2007: http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/30/weekinreview/30mydans.html

Human Rights Watch criticizes oil and gas companies for propping up the junta:
http://www.hrw.org/campaigns/burma/drilling/Burma_table3_companies.pdf

Total defends its presence in Myanmar (Burma):
http://burma.total.com/
http://burma.total.com/en/news/p_5_4.htm
http://burma.total.com/en/publications/burma_campaign.pdf
</r_sources>
        <co_id>3</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>22</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2008-01-03 20:33:26</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>103</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>10</r_score>
        <r_comment>On November 19, 2007, Human Rights Watch (HRW) released a report criticizing oil and gas companies for operating in Myanmar (Burma) and consequently providing a “crucial source of support” to the military junta that controls the government.  I have read arguments by various oil and gas companies that defend their continued operations in Myanmar, but in my opinion HRW’s critique is more persuasive.  HRW makes a strong case that these business operations directly benefit the junta to the detriment of the people of Myanmar. (I discuss both arguments below.)  

BP does not operate in Myanmar.  I therefore give BP a score of 10 for its performance in Investment &amp; Procurement Practices, recognizing that BP may exhibit different performance in other countries or in other aspects of investments and procurements.  

Since I am focusing on one country of operations here, I simply award a zero to companies that operate in Myanmar, such as Total, Chevron and Sinopec.  I award a 10 to companies that do not operate in Myanmar, such as BP, ConocoPhillips, ExxonMobil and Royal Dutch Shell.

The following excerpts from HRW’s report are worth quoting at length, because they explain how these oil and gas business deals work:

“Foreign companies sign contracts with the state-run Myanmar Oil and Gas Enterprise (MOGE). Under these contracts, the companies get permission to drill for oil and gas in a designated geographic area known as a block… The “production-sharing contracts” between MOGE and the companies specify the fees and taxes the companies have to pay to the government of Burma. They also give the government the right to become a partner in the project after a period of time, if it looks promising. In other words, foreign companies spend money up front to explore for and produce petroleum, but Burma’s military gets a cut of the sale of oil and gas produced from these fields once initial costs are recovered… Burma’s military government relies heavily on the oil and gas sector to sustain itself in power. It earned approximately $2.16 billion in 2006 from sales of natural gas, which accounted for half of Burma’s exports and represents its single largest source of foreign exchange.” 
 
Of the oil and gas companies that do operate in Myanmar, Total provides the most eloquent defense.  Other companies, such as Daewoo, dismiss criticism with such crude remarks as “Politics is politics.  Economics is economics” (as reported by HRW).  Here is what Total has to say about its operations in Myanmar:

“We are convinced that through our presence we are helping to improve the daily lives of tens of thousands of people who benefit from our social and economic initiatives. By promoting responsible behavior, our local teams can serve as a model for business and political leaders looking for ways to address the country's human rights issues.

We would like to thank all those who have encouraged us to pursue our actions to help the local people and enhance their well-being through the defense of common values. To those who ask us to leave the country, we reply that far from solving Myanmar's problems, a forced withdrawal would only lead to our replacement by other operators probably less committed to the ethical principles guiding all our initiatives. Our departure could cause the population even greater hardship and is thus an unacceptable risk.”

This pragmatic argument might be compelling if we believed that an “ethical” company like Total has a net positive impact on the people of Myanmar.  But HRW points out that the very presence of these oil and gas companies (including Total) sustains the oppressive junta that has ruined the entire country.  It’s hard to imagine how any localized benefits from business operations can outweigh the overwhelming social costs of financially supporting the junta.

You can read more about Total’s position by following the links I provide below in “Sources.”  Total’s comments are interesting, but – in my opinion – ultimately unpersuasive when compared to HRW’s critique.  And since Total has tried harder than any other company to justify its continued presence in Myanmar, I doubt that you will find good reasons to support any company in operating there. 
</r_comment>
        <r_sources>NY Times on the monk protests and junta crackdown in September 2007: http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/30/weekinreview/30mydans.html

Human Rights Watch criticizes oil and gas companies for propping up the junta:
http://www.hrw.org/campaigns/burma/drilling/Burma_table3_companies.pdf

Total defends its presence in Myanmar (Burma):
http://burma.total.com/
http://burma.total.com/en/news/p_5_4.htm
http://burma.total.com/en/publications/burma_campaign.pdf
</r_sources>
        <co_id>1</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>22</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2008-01-03 20:34:42</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>104</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>10</r_score>
        <r_comment>On November 19, 2007, Human Rights Watch (HRW) released a report criticizing oil and gas companies for operating in Myanmar (Burma) and consequently providing a “crucial source of support” to the military junta that controls the government.  I have read arguments by various oil and gas companies that defend their continued operations in Myanmar, but in my opinion HRW’s critique is more persuasive.  HRW makes a strong case that these business operations directly benefit the junta to the detriment of the people of Myanmar. (I discuss both arguments below.)  

ExxonMobil does not operate in Myanmar.  I therefore give ExxonMobil a score of 10 for its performance in Investment &amp; Procurement Practices, recognizing that ExxonMobil may exhibit different performance in other countries or in other aspects of investments and procurements.  

Since I am focusing on one country of operations here, I simply award a zero to companies that operate in Myanmar, such as Total, Chevron and Sinopec.  I award a 10 to companies that do not operate in Myanmar, such as BP, ConocoPhillips, ExxonMobil and Royal Dutch Shell.

The following excerpts from HRW’s report are worth quoting at length, because they explain how these oil and gas business deals work:

“Foreign companies sign contracts with the state-run Myanmar Oil and Gas Enterprise (MOGE). Under these contracts, the companies get permission to drill for oil and gas in a designated geographic area known as a block… The “production-sharing contracts” between MOGE and the companies specify the fees and taxes the companies have to pay to the government of Burma. They also give the government the right to become a partner in the project after a period of time, if it looks promising. In other words, foreign companies spend money up front to explore for and produce petroleum, but Burma’s military gets a cut of the sale of oil and gas produced from these fields once initial costs are recovered… Burma’s military government relies heavily on the oil and gas sector to sustain itself in power. It earned approximately $2.16 billion in 2006 from sales of natural gas, which accounted for half of Burma’s exports and represents its single largest source of foreign exchange.” 
 
Of the oil and gas companies that do operate in Myanmar, Total provides the most eloquent defense.  Other companies, such as Daewoo, dismiss criticism with such crude remarks as “Politics is politics.  Economics is economics” (as reported by HRW).  Here is what Total has to say about its operations in Myanmar:

“We are convinced that through our presence we are helping to improve the daily lives of tens of thousands of people who benefit from our social and economic initiatives. By promoting responsible behavior, our local teams can serve as a model for business and political leaders looking for ways to address the country's human rights issues.

We would like to thank all those who have encouraged us to pursue our actions to help the local people and enhance their well-being through the defense of common values. To those who ask us to leave the country, we reply that far from solving Myanmar's problems, a forced withdrawal would only lead to our replacement by other operators probably less committed to the ethical principles guiding all our initiatives. Our departure could cause the population even greater hardship and is thus an unacceptable risk.”

This pragmatic argument might be compelling if we believed that an “ethical” company like Total has a net positive impact on the people of Myanmar.  But HRW points out that the very presence of these oil and gas companies (including Total) sustains the oppressive junta that has ruined the entire country.  It’s hard to imagine how any localized benefits from business operations can outweigh the overwhelming social costs of financially supporting the junta.

You can read more about Total’s position by following the links I provide below in “Sources.”  Total’s comments are interesting, but – in my opinion – ultimately unpersuasive when compared to HRW’s critique.  And since Total has tried harder than any other company to justify its continued presence in Myanmar, I doubt that you will find good reasons to support any company in operating there. 
</r_comment>
        <r_sources>NY Times on the monk protests and junta crackdown in September 2007: http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/30/weekinreview/30mydans.html

Human Rights Watch criticizes oil and gas companies for propping up the junta:
http://www.hrw.org/campaigns/burma/drilling/Burma_table3_companies.pdf

Total defends its presence in Myanmar (Burma):
http://burma.total.com/
http://burma.total.com/en/news/p_5_4.htm
http://burma.total.com/en/publications/burma_campaign.pdf
</r_sources>
        <co_id>4</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>22</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2008-01-03 20:35:53</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>105</r_id>
        <uname>dmagida</uname>
        <r_score>9</r_score>
        <r_comment>P&amp;G has continued to receive deserved recognition of its Children's Safe Drinking Water program. On Dev 5, 2007, P&amp;G won the Ron Brown Award for Corporate Leadership for this program. This Safe Drinking Water Program has already delivered 860 million liters of clean water in 30 countries. The goal is that by 2012 this program will deliver 2 billion liters per year of clean water thereby saving an estimated 10,000 lives. </r_comment>
        <r_sources>Dec 5, 2007 press release (at White House Ceremony) by The Ron Brown Award for Corporate Leadership. </r_sources>
        <co_id>12</co_id>
        <cat_id>5</cat_id>
        <top_id>19</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2008-01-04 06:28:04</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>106</r_id>
        <uname></uname>
        <r_score>2</r_score>
        <r_comment>Much of this is cited directly from http://www.kleercut.net/en/.

&quot;A new Greenpeace report reveals that Kimberly-Clark devastated Ontario’s Kenogami Forest while promoting itself as a leader in environmental and social responsibility.

Cut and Run uses government information, independent audits, public records, and satellite mapping to document Kimberly-Clark’s management and logging of the Kenogami Forest near Thunder Bay, Ontario. It details how, in just 70 years, the Kenogami Forest has been turned from a vast expanse of healthy, near-pristine forest, to a severely damaged landscape rife with social and environmental problems--largely to make products that are used once and then thrown away.

Much of the virgin tree fibre Kimberly-Clark uses for its tissue products come from unsustainably managed forests. These forests are predominantly logged in clearcuts — a devastating form of logging where most if not all trees are removed from an area of forest.

What’s left behind is a barren landscape that can no longer support wildlife species, such as wolverines, bears, caribou, wolves and the billions of birds that depend on ancient forests for their survival.&quot;</r_comment>
        <r_sources>Greenpeace

http://www.kleercut.net/en/</r_sources>
        <co_id>10</co_id>
        <cat_id>2</cat_id>
        <top_id>15</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2008-05-29 15:48:27</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>107</r_id>
        <uname>sdemessieres</uname>
        <r_score>8</r_score>
        <r_comment>Henkel's Sustainability Report 2007 reports substantial progress on some goals since 2003, including - according to a summary by Ethical Performance.com - a 57 per cent decline in heavy metals released per metric tonne of output, a 21 per cent fall in energy consumption and a 72 per cent reduction in occupational accidents.

A 21 per cent decline in energy consumption is a substantial accomplishment.  I'm also glad to hear that Henkel has made public commitments to further reduce their energy consumption and related carbon dioxide emissions by 15 percent and to cut water consumption and waste generation by 10 per cent each by 2012, compared to 2007 levels.

Few people would trust a corporate citizenship report as much as an independent third-party assessment, and I'm no exception.  But companies that fail to report accurately or accomplish stated goals can suffer backlash to their brand.  Companies can even be held liable for false advertising if their reports are inaccurate, so I'm fairly confident in the accuracy of these reports.  (Nike Inc. vs. Kasky was a precedent; see http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nike,_Inc.#Kasky_v._Nike)  

</r_comment>
        <r_sources>http://www.ethicalperformance.com/reports/reportdetail.php?reportid=47</r_sources>
        <co_id>9</co_id>
        <cat_id>2</cat_id>
        <top_id>15</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2008-06-26 10:30:21</enter_dt>
    </review>
    <review>
        <r_id>108</r_id>
        <uname></uname>
        <r_score>0</r_score>
        <r_comment></r_comment>
        <r_sources></r_sources>
        <co_id>0</co_id>
        <cat_id>0</cat_id>
        <top_id>0</top_id>
        <enter_dt>2008-06-28 06:35:22</enter_dt>
    </review>
  <!-- Table user -->
    <user>
        <u_id>1</u_id>
        <u_name>lcrowley</u_name>
        <u_pword>lcrowley</u_pword>
        <fname>Lisa</fname>
        <lname>Crowley</lname>
        <email>me@me.com</email>
        <zip>01915</zip>
        <gender>f</gender>
        <agi>250</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>123</u_id>
        <u_name>swaddock</u_name>
        <u_pword>swaddock</u_pword>
        <fname>Sandra</fname>
        <lname>Waddock</lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>122</u_id>
        <u_name>gbloom</u_name>
        <u_pword>gbloom</u_pword>
        <fname>Gordon</fname>
        <lname>Bloom</lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>2</u_id>
        <u_name>jenn</u_name>
        <u_pword>jenn</u_pword>
        <fname>Jennifer</fname>
        <lname>Sullivan</lname>
        <email>js@jsdesigns.com</email>
        <zip>094554</zip>
        <gender>f</gender>
        <agi>1000000</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>3</u_id>
        <u_name>chris</u_name>
        <u_pword>lisa</u_pword>
        <fname>Christopher</fname>
        <lname>Crowley</lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>196</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>120</u_id>
        <u_name>pherman</u_name>
        <u_pword>pherman</u_pword>
        <fname>R. Paul</fname>
        <lname>Herman</lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>4</u_id>
        <u_name>sdemessieres</u_name>
        <u_pword>Cmilo890</u_pword>
        <fname>Stephane</fname>
        <lname>de Messieres</lname>
        <email>sdemessieres@citizensmarket.org</email>
        <zip>02139</zip>
        <gender>M</gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>193</u_id>
        <u_name>itscool</u_name>
        <u_pword>2pert3f</u_pword>
        <fname>Andrew</fname>
        <lname>Varyu</lname>
        <email>founder@itscool.us</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>192</u_id>
        <u_name>thomviolence</u_name>
        <u_pword>vxaxs</u_pword>
        <fname>Thomas</fname>
        <lname>Grant</lname>
        <email>thomviolence@hotmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>5</u_id>
        <u_name>jlassman</u_name>
        <u_pword>elvis</u_pword>
        <fname>Justine</fname>
        <lname>Lassman</lname>
        <email>justinelassman@yahoo.com</email>
        <zip>02139</zip>
        <gender>F</gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>191</u_id>
        <u_name>sharonc</u_name>
        <u_pword>merong</u_pword>
        <fname>Sharon</fname>
        <lname>Chae</lname>
        <email>sharon.chae@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>6</u_id>
        <u_name>kmagida</u_name>
        <u_pword>kmagida</u_pword>
        <fname>Kyle</fname>
        <lname>Magida</lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>7</u_id>
        <u_name>iwohl</u_name>
        <u_pword>iwohl</u_pword>
        <fname>Isaac</fname>
        <lname>Wohl</lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>8</u_id>
        <u_name>dcate</u_name>
        <u_pword>dcate</u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>9</u_id>
        <u_name>dmagida</u_name>
        <u_pword>dmagida</u_pword>
        <fname>David</fname>
        <lname>Magida</lname>
        <email>davem@norwich.edu</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>190</u_id>
        <u_name>gwohl</u_name>
        <u_pword>rosalie</u_pword>
        <fname>gabe</fname>
        <lname>wohl</lname>
        <email>gwohl@hotmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>10</u_id>
        <u_name>klee</u_name>
        <u_pword>klee</u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>124</u_id>
        <u_name>cjochnick</u_name>
        <u_pword>cjochnick</u_pword>
        <fname>Chris</fname>
        <lname>Jochnick</lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>125</u_id>
        <u_name>aebrahim</u_name>
        <u_pword>aebrahim</u_pword>
        <fname>Alnoor</fname>
        <lname>Ebrahim</lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>126</u_id>
        <u_name>mpirson</u_name>
        <u_pword>mpirson</u_pword>
        <fname>Michael</fname>
        <lname>Pirson</lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>189</u_id>
        <u_name>jhoney</u_name>
        <u_pword>yepoi</u_pword>
        <fname>Jordi</fname>
        <lname>Honey-Roses</lname>
        <email>jhoney@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>188</u_id>
        <u_name>asalwin</u_name>
        <u_pword>aesaes</u_pword>
        <fname>Arthur</fname>
        <lname>Salwin</lname>
        <email>asalwin@juno.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>187</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname>Sheldon</fname>
        <lname>Brown</lname>
        <email>sbrown3@norwich.edu</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>186</u_id>
        <u_name>Liptakaa</u_name>
        <u_pword>Trilobite</u_pword>
        <fname>Andrew</fname>
        <lname>Liptak</lname>
        <email>JediTrilobite@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>134</u_id>
        <u_name>tpinkerton</u_name>
        <u_pword>tpinkerton</u_pword>
        <fname>Todd</fname>
        <lname>Pinkerton</lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>185</u_id>
        <u_name>Liptakaa</u_name>
        <u_pword>Trilobite</u_pword>
        <fname>Andrew</fname>
        <lname>Liptak</lname>
        <email>JediTrilobite@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>184</u_id>
        <u_name>bfinck</u_name>
        <u_pword>camber</u_pword>
        <fname>Bobbi-Jo</fname>
        <lname>Finck</lname>
        <email>bfinck@norwich.edu</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>140</u_id>
        <u_name>cmg</u_name>
        <u_pword>cmg</u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>183</u_id>
        <u_name>ndidomen</u_name>
        <u_pword>tanzania</u_pword>
        <fname>Nicole</fname>
        <lname>DiDomenico</lname>
        <email>ndidomen@yahoo.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>142</u_id>
        <u_name>toddp</u_name>
        <u_pword>hello</u_pword>
        <fname>Todd</fname>
        <lname>Pinkerton</lname>
        <email>todd.pinkerton@gmail.com</email>
        <zip>01243</zip>
        <gender>M</gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>182</u_id>
        <u_name>jbmeadvin</u_name>
        <u_pword>6jdmjjl6</u_pword>
        <fname>Joanna</fname>
        <lname>Meadvin</lname>
        <email>jbmeadvin@hotmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>181</u_id>
        <u_name>Tone</u_name>
        <u_pword>chancydog</u_pword>
        <fname>Anthony</fname>
        <lname>Lovell</lname>
        <email>tone@dreadnoughtproject.org</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>180</u_id>
        <u_name>kariormo</u_name>
        <u_pword>potomac</u_pword>
        <fname>kari</fname>
        <lname>wilner</lname>
        <email>kari.wilner@wfp.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>149</u_id>
        <u_name>jason</u_name>
        <u_pword>qwas</u_pword>
        <fname>jason</fname>
        <lname>mills</lname>
        <email>ibez@inmail24.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>150</u_id>
        <u_name>dan.toomey</u_name>
        <u_pword>asdf1asdf</u_pword>
        <fname>Dan</fname>
        <lname>Toomey</lname>
        <email>dan@dantoomeysoftware.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>151</u_id>
        <u_name>lucy</u_name>
        <u_pword>aesop</u_pword>
        <fname>lucy</fname>
        <lname>mendel</lname>
        <email>lucy@thoughtandmemory.org</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>179</u_id>
        <u_name>tannenprintz</u_name>
        <u_pword>gremmy42</u_pword>
        <fname>Tannen</fname>
        <lname>Printz</lname>
        <email>tannen.printz@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>178</u_id>
        <u_name>greg@fotonotes.</u_name>
        <u_pword>vermontkitty</u_pword>
        <fname>Greg</fname>
        <lname>Elin</lname>
        <email>greg@fotonotes.net</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>177</u_id>
        <u_name>mbcccj</u_name>
        <u_pword>1cin88ger3</u_pword>
        <fname>Lennie</fname>
        <lname>Magida</lname>
        <email>lennmag@verizon.net</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>176</u_id>
        <u_name>davew</u_name>
        <u_pword>dwrugby</u_pword>
        <fname>David</fname>
        <lname>Whaley</lname>
        <email>davew@norwich.edu</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>160</u_id>
        <u_name>irislawrence</u_name>
        <u_pword>daradolls</u_pword>
        <fname>Iris</fname>
        <lname>Lawrence</lname>
        <email>IRISLAWRENCE@YAHOO.COM</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>161</u_id>
        <u_name>clayward</u_name>
        <u_pword>fozzy</u_pword>
        <fname>clay</fname>
        <lname>ward</lname>
        <email>clay@thoughtandmemory.org</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>162</u_id>
        <u_name>Graham Bullock</u_name>
        <u_pword>citizensmarket</u_pword>
        <fname>Graham</fname>
        <lname>Bullock</lname>
        <email>graham7@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>163</u_id>
        <u_name>ryan</u_name>
        <u_pword>sandiego</u_pword>
        <fname>Ryan</fname>
        <lname>Mickle</lname>
        <email>ryan@dotherightthing.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>164</u_id>
        <u_name>mexileleon</u_name>
        <u_pword>pollux</u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email>gaudierl@yahoo.fr</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>165</u_id>
        <u_name>vanessiaw</u_name>
        <u_pword>mp04pb</u_pword>
        <fname>vanessia</fname>
        <lname>Wu</lname>
        <email>vanessia@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>167</u_id>
        <u_name>foo</u_name>
        <u_pword>bar</u_pword>
        <fname>foo</fname>
        <lname>bar</lname>
        <email>foo@bar.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>168</u_id>
        <u_name>foo</u_name>
        <u_pword>bar</u_pword>
        <fname>foo</fname>
        <lname>bar</lname>
        <email>foo@bar.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>175</u_id>
        <u_name>robinumd</u_name>
        <u_pword>Rlt9260</u_pword>
        <fname>Robin</fname>
        <lname>Toblin</lname>
        <email>rtoblin@yahoo.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>174</u_id>
        <u_name>vmlassman</u_name>
        <u_pword>scotland</u_pword>
        <fname>vivienne</fname>
        <lname>lassman</lname>
        <email>vmlassman@juno.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>194</u_id>
        <u_name>susannebg</u_name>
        <u_pword>daddyyy0</u_pword>
        <fname>Susanne</fname>
        <lname>Goldstein</lname>
        <email>susannebg@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>197</u_id>
        <u_name>pablosur</u_name>
        <u_pword>PIREpire0</u_pword>
        <fname>Pablo</fname>
        <lname>Suarez</lname>
        <email>suarez@bu.edu</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>198</u_id>
        <u_name>Sporky023</u_name>
        <u_pword>budapest</u_pword>
        <fname>Luke</fname>
        <lname>Griffiths</lname>
        <email>wlgriffiths@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>199</u_id>
        <u_name>xiann</u_name>
        <u_pword>tummydoor</u_pword>
        <fname>Christian</fname>
        <lname>MacAuley</lname>
        <email>csm@xiann.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>200</u_id>
        <u_name>BigWilly77</u_name>
        <u_pword>f3v3r</u_pword>
        <fname>Marshall</fname>
        <lname>Browning</lname>
        <email>marshall.browning@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>201</u_id>
        <u_name>cikanaam</u_name>
        <u_pword>escort1</u_pword>
        <fname>eric</fname>
        <lname>scott</lname>
        <email>puppy_chow12@yahoo.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>202</u_id>
        <u_name>Luke</u_name>
        <u_pword>budapest</u_pword>
        <fname>Luke</fname>
        <lname>Griffiths</lname>
        <email>lgriffiths@citizensmarket.org</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>203</u_id>
        <u_name>beakedprow</u_name>
        <u_pword>homebound</u_pword>
        <fname>Olivier</fname>
        <lname>de Messières</lname>
        <email>ilivier1@demessieres.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>204</u_id>
        <u_name>robbygrossman</u_name>
        <u_pword>gomets</u_pword>
        <fname>Robby</fname>
        <lname>Grossman</lname>
        <email>therealrobby@robbygrossman.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>205</u_id>
        <u_name>salbinati</u_name>
        <u_pword>claro9</u_pword>
        <fname>Stephen</fname>
        <lname>Albinati</lname>
        <email>stephen.albinati@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>206</u_id>
        <u_name>ericmelin</u_name>
        <u_pword>lifelife</u_pword>
        <fname>Eric</fname>
        <lname>Melin</lname>
        <email>ericmelin@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>207</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>208</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>209</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>210</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>211</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>212</u_id>
        <u_name>rharper</u_name>
        <u_pword>richard</u_pword>
        <fname>Richard</fname>
        <lname>Harper</lname>
        <email>richardharper@optonline.net</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>213</u_id>
        <u_name>luxllt</u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname>luxllt</fname>
        <lname>luxllt</lname>
        <email>fnzjuj@jeysge.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>214</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>215</u_id>
        <u_name>Maemae</u_name>
        <u_pword>mae2357</u_pword>
        <fname>Megan</fname>
        <lname>Kilcoyne</lname>
        <email>megan.kilcoyne@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>216</u_id>
        <u_name>jheydenr</u_name>
        <u_pword>damnation</u_pword>
        <fname>Juliette</fname>
        <lname>Heydenrych</lname>
        <email>juliette.christine@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>217</u_id>
        <u_name>dazeymaisy</u_name>
        <u_pword>ilovemichael</u_pword>
        <fname>Jessica</fname>
        <lname>Spence</lname>
        <email>dazeymaisy@hotmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>218</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>219</u_id>
        <u_name>Luke</u_name>
        <u_pword>arch-type</u_pword>
        <fname>Luke</fname>
        <lname>Griffiths</lname>
        <email>wlgriffiths@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>220</u_id>
        <u_name>someginger</u_name>
        <u_pword>meliza11</u_pword>
        <fname>Genevieve</fname>
        <lname>de Messieres</lname>
        <email>someginger@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>221</u_id>
        <u_name>dlw</u_name>
        <u_pword>hihohi</u_pword>
        <fname>Daniel</fname>
        <lname>Weinreb</lname>
        <email>dlw@alum.mit.edu</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>222</u_id>
        <u_name>dan_illustratio</u_name>
        <u_pword>positive</u_pword>
        <fname>Dan</fname>
        <lname>Osterman</lname>
        <email>dan_illustration@yahoo.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>223</u_id>
        <u_name>KSrinivasan</u_name>
        <u_pword>elephant</u_pword>
        <fname>Kavita</fname>
        <lname>Srinivasan</lname>
        <email>kavita_sridhar@ksg07.harvard.edu</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>224</u_id>
        <u_name>wwhcoz</u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname>wwhcoz</fname>
        <lname>wwhcoz</lname>
        <email>hjdjgs@wyuxzk.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>225</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>226</u_id>
        <u_name>oleuglmobn</u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname>oleuglmobn</fname>
        <lname>oleuglmobn</lname>
        <email>zqrdoh@zorbpx.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>227</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>228</u_id>
        <u_name>gregtidwell</u_name>
        <u_pword>teri312</u_pword>
        <fname>Greg</fname>
        <lname>Tidwell</lname>
        <email>greg.tidwell@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>229</u_id>
        <u_name>toniacapuana</u_name>
        <u_pword>nteallmp</u_pword>
        <fname>tonia</fname>
        <lname>capuana</lname>
        <email>toniacapuana@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>230</u_id>
        <u_name>Timothy468</u_name>
        <u_pword>mdnsba12</u_pword>
        <fname>Timothy</fname>
        <lname>Murphy</lname>
        <email>tim468@yahoo.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>231</u_id>
        <u_name>Timothy468</u_name>
        <u_pword>mdnsba12</u_pword>
        <fname>Timothy</fname>
        <lname>Murphy</lname>
        <email>tim468@yahoo.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>232</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>233</u_id>
        <u_name>wahyuy</u_name>
        <u_pword>9601100189104</u_pword>
        <fname>wah</fname>
        <lname>yu</lname>
        <email>wahyuy@yahoo.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>234</u_id>
        <u_name>gammagrace</u_name>
        <u_pword>123456</u_pword>
        <fname>grace</fname>
        <lname>mathews</lname>
        <email>grace@gammagraphics.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>235</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>236</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>237</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>238</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>239</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>240</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>241</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>242</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>243</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>244</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>245</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>246</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>247</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>248</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>249</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>250</u_id>
        <u_name></u_name>
        <u_pword></u_pword>
        <fname></fname>
        <lname></lname>
        <email></email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>0</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>251</u_id>
        <u_name>subakva</u_name>
        <u_pword>peerahtay</u_pword>
        <fname>Jason</fname>
        <lname>Wadsworth</lname>
        <email>jdwadsworth@gmail.com</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
    <user>
        <u_id>252</u_id>
        <u_name>aoeisenb</u_name>
        <u_pword>p455w0Rd</u_pword>
        <fname>Alexandria</fname>
        <lname>Eisenbarth</lname>
        <email>aoeisenb@fas.harvard.edu</email>
        <zip></zip>
        <gender></gender>
        <agi>0</agi>
        <u_type></u_type>
        <ecommunity>1</ecommunity>
    </user>
  <!-- Table user_cat -->
    <user_cat>
        <u_id>61</u_id>
        <top_id>16</top_id>
        <importance>4</importance>
        <weight>0.666667</weight>
    </user_cat>
    <user_cat>
        <u_id>61</u_id>
        <top_id>15</top_id>
        <importance>2</importance>
        <weight>0.333333</weight>
    </user_cat>
    <user_cat>
        <u_id>1</u_id>
        <top_id>20</top_id>
        <importance>9</importance>
        <weight>0.29</weight>
    </user_cat>
    <user_cat>
        <u_id>1</u_id>
        <top_id>19</top_id>
        <importance>5</importance>
        <weight>0.16</weight>
    </user_cat>
    <user_cat>
        <u_id>1</u_id>
        <top_id>17</top_id>
        <importance>7</importance>
        <weight>0.23</weight>
    </user_cat>
    <user_cat>
        <u_id>1</u_id>
        <top_id>16</top_id>
        <importance>5</importance>
        <weight>0.16129</weight>
    </user_cat>
    <user_cat>
        <u_id>1</u_id>
        <top_id>15</top_id>
        <importance>5</importance>
        <weight>0.16129</weight>
    </user_cat>
</citizensmarket>
